here.
ここ。
learn how to play yatown
ヤタウンの遊び方を学ぶ
bien hungry
お腹がとっても空いてる
Through rich
豊かさを通して
ring
指輪
applause
拍手
Thank you.
ありがとう。
Vice President Peng Xuming was supposed to host today
彭暁明副主席が今日の司会を務める予定だった
But because he just took office
しかし就任したばかりなので
Then he has traveled with people before
それから彼は以前に人々と一緒に旅行したことがあります
It was already ordered
すでに注文されていました
so he can't come tonight
だから彼は今夜は来られない
I want to help him host
彼のホストを手伝いたい
then today's
それから今日の
This topic is of great interest
このトピックは非常に興味深いです
Issues that have attracted great attention in the past ten or twenty years
ここ10年、20年で大きな注目を集めた問題
it's climate change
それは気候変動です
I want to talk about climate change twenty years ago
20年前の気候変動について話したい
When environmental changes talk about these things
環境の変化がこれらのことを語るとき
At that time, these seemed relatively foreign to at least some people.
当時、少なくとも一部の人々にとって、これらは比較的異質なものに見えました。
But now it has become very urgent
しかし今では非常に緊急性が高くなりました
The first three weeks of our Academia Sinica
中央研究院の最初の 3 週間
In this place in Thailand, the Pacific Institute of Science and Technology is organized
タイのこの場所に、太平洋科学技術大学が設立されています。
PNC
PNC
In Bangkok, it happened to encounter this flood problem
バンコクではたまたまこの洪水問題に遭遇しました
So this makes people feel that this issue is very urgent
このため、人々はこの問題が非常に緊急であると感じます
So we are at Academia Sinica these days
それで私たちは最近中央研究院にいます
In addition to the feast of knowledge tonight
今夜の知識の饗宴に加えて
We have an environmental history at the Renwen Pavilion
人文パビリオンには環境の歴史があります
Conference on World Environmental History
世界環境史会議
It's also worth going
それも行く価値があります
Today we invited the speaker is this
本日お招きしたスピーカーはこちら
Inter-director of the Special Review Researcher of the Environmental Change Center of the Academia Sinica
特別審査所長兼中央研究院環境変化センター研究員
Professor Liu Shaocheng
劉少成教授
Professor Liu is a member of the School of Physics at Cheng Kung University
Liu 教授は成功大学物理学部のメンバーです
Go to PizBall University in the United States to get a Ph.D. in physics
物理学の博士号を取得するために米国のピズボール大学に行く
Since then he has stayed in the United States to work
それ以来、彼は仕事のため米国に滞在している
U.S. Oceanographic Service
米国海洋局
Research Director of Daji Physics Laboratory
大慈物理研究所 研究部長
also served at the Georgia Institute of Technology
ジョージア工科大学でも勤務
Chair Professor of the School of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences
地球大気科学部 教授
department head
部長
He returned to the China Security Research Institute 12 years ago
彼は12年前に中国安全保障研究所に戻った
That horse was first on Earth
あの馬は地球上に初めて現れた
Then came the creation of the Environmental Center
その後、環境センターが設立されました。
if memory serves me right
記憶が正しければ
Gore won the Nobel Peace Prize
ゴア氏がノーベル平和賞を受賞
There seem to be more than 1000
1000以上あるらしい
Contributors also get a certificate
貢献者も証明書を取得できます
Director Liu also got a
リュー監督も受賞しました
It can be seen that he has participated in the concern for a long time
彼が長い間この懸念に参加してきたことがわかる
There are also research contributions in this area
この分野の研究貢献もあります
We have gained great international
私たちは素晴らしい国際性を獲得しました
recall and affirm
思い出して肯定する
I am very happy to have the opportunity to invite him to give a speech today
今日は彼をスピーチに招待する機会を得てとてもうれしく思います
And he's talking about the topics he's good at
そして彼は自分の得意な話題について話しています
climate change in taiwan
台湾の気候変動
The subtitle is Shock Mitigation and Adaptation
サブタイトルは「ショックの緩和と適応」
We now applaud Professor Liu
私たちは今、劉教授に拍手を送ります
applause applause
拍手、拍手
Vice President Wang
王副院長
Everyone advanced
全員が進歩しました
Colleagues
同僚
Ladies
レディース
hello gentlemen
こんにちは皆さん
global warming climate change
地球温暖化 気候変動
I believe everyone has heard it many times
誰もが何度も聞いたことがあると思います
I was actually a feast of knowledge in 2004
2004 年、私は実際に知識の饗宴でした
Also talked about a topic quite related to this topic
この話題に関連する話題についても話しました
Actually today when I was preparing
実は今日準備をしていた時に
Today I
今日私は
I said that I must be completely different from that film in 2004.
2004年のあの映画とは全く違うはずだと言いました。
ah
ああ
No
いいえ
Of course, there will always be a few articles, and I counted them.
もちろん、常にいくつかの記事が存在するので、数えてみました。
15% of the films are pretty close to last time
15% の映画は前回とほぼ同じです
No
いいえ
This time this year
今年のこの時期は
I'll show you guys look at our first one this one this one is very different
最初のものを見てみましょう、これは非常に異なります
In fact, what do I say about that, that, and this movie?
実際、あのこと、あのこと、そしてこの映画について何を言えばいいでしょうか？
Tell me, introduce me, introduce us to you
私たちについて話して、紹介して、教えてください
this is gone
これはなくなった
Whoops
おっと
ah
ああ
I'm afraid I can make a brighter one, and this one is basically invisible.
もっと明るいものを作ることができますが、これは基本的に見えません。
I want to go to the back. This is basically the introduction.
奥に行きたいのですが、基本的には導入です。
This is, of course, the history that Vice President Wang is most familiar with.
もちろん、これは王副総統が最もよく知っている歴史である。
OK Human Evolution History
OK 人類の進化の歴史
The first green one is Lucy
最初の緑色はルーシーです
You see Lucy is very interesting
ルーシーはとても興味深いですね
I believe everyone has heard
誰もが聞いたことがあると思います
Africa's first dug
アフリカ初の掘削
Lucy who looks like a human
人間に見えるルーシー
We suppose are all its descendants
私たちは全員がその子孫だと考えています
Everyone also noticed that the original people in Beijing were
北京にもともといた人々は、
This is about 3 million years
これは約300万年です
Peking Man was less than 1 million years old
北京原人の年齢は100万歳未満だった
800,000 years
80万年
Then Homo sapiens was almost 200,000 years ago
それからホモ・サピエンスは約20万年前です
And then until Homo sapiens came out
そしてホモ・サピエンスが現れるまで
not exodus
出エジプトではない
After leaving Africa
アフリカを出国後
Then the first most important historical
次に、最初の最も重要な歴史的
what happened was
何が起こったのか
Ancient civilization
古文明
Everyone probably knows about ancient civilizations that there are four ancient civilizations
古代文明については、4つの古代文明があることは誰もが知っているでしょう。
Since Father Wang is here, I won’t ask you what the four are.
王神父がここにいるので、4つが何なのかは聞きません。
Originally, I thought it was because Father Wang knew too well
当初は王神父がよく知っているからだと思っていた
So I won't bring up this question any more
だからもうこの質問は取り上げないよ
Ancient civilization
古文明
Of course including China iQi
もちろん中国iQiも含めて
basically in almost
基本的にはほぼ
That is to say, from four thousand years to almost eight thousand years
つまり、4000年から8000年近くまで
developed
発展した
From a climate point of view
気候の観点から見ると
human evolution
人類の進化
Now here I am a
今ここに私はいます
This is time and this is temperature
これが時間で、ここが温度です
zero degrees here
ここはゼロ度
OK
OK
Of course, this so-called zero degree is only used to represent
もちろん、このいわゆるゼロ度は、次のことを表すためにのみ使用されます。
is the current temperature before the industrial revolution
産業革命前の現在の気温です
because zero is here
ゼロがここにいるから
this is two degrees this is minus two degrees
これは 2 度です これはマイナス 2 度です
OK
OK
Of course the dinosaurs were hot
もちろん恐竜は暑かったです
this is it
これだよ
But what we just saw
しかし、私たちがたった今見たのは
Ha, this ancient civilization is almost
ああ、この古代文明はもうすぐです。
ah
ああ
About five, six, five, or six thousand years ago
約5、6、5、6000年前
ha
はぁ
it's here
ここにあります
OK
OK
this paragraph
この段落
this paragraph now
今この段落
Of course, it is called the best period of the new climate.
もちろん新気候の最盛期とも言われます。
OK
OK
ah
ああ
Then why is this the best period for a new climate?
では、なぜこの時期が新しい気候に最適な時期なのでしょうか？
it has its reasons
それには理由があります
at that time
その時
it's time again
また時間が来たよ
OK
OK
it's four thousand years
四千年だ
ten thousand years you see
1万年後が見えます
four thousand to ten thousand years
4千年から1万年
you look at the northern hemisphere
あなたは北半球を見ています
all red and yellow
全部赤と黄色
all on average
すべて平均して
Middle and high latitudes of the northern hemisphere
北半球の中緯度および高緯度
almost two degrees
ほぼ2度
this ratio
この比率
more than two degrees higher than now
現在より2度以上高い
But in the low-dimensional sea
でも低次元の海では
Ocean temperatures are relatively low
海水温は比較的低い
So what I just showed you is here
それで、私が今お見せしたものはここにあります
This is the best time for the new climate
新しい気候に最適な時期です
The best period is of course when the northern hemisphere was very warm just now
もちろん、北半球がちょうど今とても暖かかった時期が最適です。
Civilization develops when it's very warm
文明は非常に暖かいときに発展する
make it easy for everyone to think of
誰もが考えやすいように
That is to say, the high temperature I showed you just now
つまり、さっき見せた高温
That is to say, two degrees higher
つまり2度高い
compared with just now
さっきと比べて
You see, we humans have been talking about 3 million years since just now
ほら、私たち人類はさっきから300万年について話し続けています
Lucy has basically been here since she started
ルーシーは基本的に、始めたときからここにいます
you see it's very cold
とても寒いのがわかりますね
cold to sometimes more than two degrees
時には2度以上の寒さになる
most of the time 80% of the time
ほとんどの場合、80%の時間
We are in a much colder super than the current
私たちは現在よりもはるかに寒い超極地にいます
almost once
ほぼ一度
develop there
そこで発展する
evolve there
そこで進化する
So from this point of view
したがって、この観点からすると
We should be very suitable
私たちはとても適しているはずです
cooler earth
冷たい地球
Than what two once looked like now
かつての二人の姿よりも今は
But once we get here, than now
でもここに来れば今よりも
hotter than we're used to
私たちが慣れているよりも暑い
culture
文化
civilization
文明
culture develops
文化が発展する
This is a very interesting phenomenon
これはとても興味深い現象です
I've actually always been interested in this
実はずっとこれに興味があったのです
Here I also show you
こちらでもご紹介させていただきます
we are now greenhouse gas
私たちは今、温室効果ガスになっています
Scenarios for temperature increase by 2100
2100年までに気温が上昇するシナリオ
It's about 2 to 4 degrees
気温は2度から4度くらいです
i draw it here
ここに描きます
2 to 4 degrees
2～4度
Everyone think about our
誰もが私たちのことを考えてください
It's almost over 2 degrees here
ここのところ気温は2度を超えています
In fact, many people say
実際、多くの人がこう言います
since we are here
私たちがここにいるから
culture develops so fast
文化はとても早く発展します
so good
とても良い
obviously the climate you see
明らかにあなたが見ている気候
this too
これも
recognized worldwide
世界中で認められている
This is not a word I invented
これは私が作った言葉ではありません
Here is another solid
こちらがもう一つの立体です
best climate
最高の気候
warmer
暖かい
OK
OK
and at that time it was true
そしてその時はそれが本当だった
The Earth's
地球的
productivity
生産性
yes
はい
it is this
これです
just say that
それを言ってください
earth creatures
地球の生き物
The situation of growth
成長状況
It is indeed very
それは本当にとても
special
非常的
how to say
どのように言って
very prosperous
とても裕福な
OK
OK
In comparison
比較において
then someone will say
そうすれば誰かが言うだろう
since we want
私たちが望んでいるから
two to four degrees hotter
2〜4度暑い
that would have been this
それはこうだったでしょう
Let's say four thousand years to almost ten thousand years ago
4000年からほぼ10000年前だと思いますか
It's so hot and so good
とても熱くてとても良いです
Then why should we worry about the future
では、なぜ将来のことを心配する必要があるのでしょうか
climate warming
気候温暖化
The problem
問題
it was brought up
それは持ち出されました
And it's actually quite interesting that a
そして実際には非常に興味深いのですが、
a very meaningful topic
とても意味のある話題
But before we go on
しかし、先に進む前に
I want to give you a little introduction
少しご紹介したいと思います
here of course we are here now
もちろんここです、私たちは今ここにいます
OK
OK
Then here it is a logarithm
次に、これは対数です
this this mark
このマーク
10,000 years from here to here
ここからここまで1万年
So the ancient civilization we are talking about is here
つまり、私たちが話している古代文明はここにあるのです
That
それか
And then this little iceberg is here
そして、この小さな氷山がここにあります
OK
OK
The other four big glacial oddities are here
他の 4 つの大きな氷河の奇妙さはここにあります
Often the previous ones are many, many, many
多くの場合、以前のものはたくさん、たくさん、たくさんあります
big and small glaciers
大小の氷河
OK
OK
ah
ああ
what does this picture mean
この絵は何を意味しますか
I'm here to tell you about
についてお話しするためにここに来ました
The flood control by heavy rain was almost 4,000 years ago
大雨による治水は約4000年前から
OK
OK
That's an interesting one here
ここは興味深いですね
Today I participated in the one mentioned by Vice President Wang just now
今日、私は先ほど王副総統が言及したイベントに参加しました。
Conference on Environmental History of East Asian History
東アジア環境史研究会
Many people mentioned the situation when the heavy rain cured the water
大雨で水が治ったときの状況について多くの人が言及しました
Yes, what I mentioned just now is about greenhouse gases
はい、私が今言ったのは温室効果ガスについてです
What if you assume different greenhouse gases
異なる温室効果ガスを仮定するとどうなるか
In the worst case scenario, the greenhouse increases by almost four degrees
最悪のシナリオでは、温室が 4 度近く温暖化する
In the best case, the temperature will increase by nearly 2 degrees.
最良の場合、気温は2度近く上昇します
So 2 degrees to 4 degrees is currently our forecast
したがって、現時点では 2 度から 4 度が予想されます
Scenarios for model-predicted warming
モデルが予測する温暖化のシナリオ
Going back to the four ancient Wenmin countries we talked about just now
先ほど話した古代文民四国の話に戻ります。
China Egypt Asia Minor
中国 エジプト 小アジア
About 4,000 to 7,000 years ago
約4000年から7000年前
developed at that time
当時開発された
Of course we just saw this and that
もちろん、私たちはあれこれ見ただけです
almost all history
ほぼすべての歴史
Scholars are talking about this
学者たちはこれについて話しています
It is said that there was a good climate at that time
当時は気候が良かったと言われています
but the problem is
しかし問題は
What exactly does a good climate environment mean?
良好な気候環境とは具体的に何を意味するのでしょうか？
Most books will say
ほとんどの本にはこう書かれています
It's very warm in the middle of the northern hemisphere
北半球の真ん中でとても暖かいです
Here I want to tell you
ここでお伝えしたいのは
Wait so everyone can see
みんなが見れるように待っててね
This answer is definitely not like this
この答えは絶対にこんなものではありません
This is actually the wrong answer
実はこれは間違った答えなのです
I don't agree with the warm climate in the middle of the northern hemisphere
私は北半球の真ん中の温暖な気候に同意しません
That is what we just mentioned
それが今お話ししたことです
This is 4,000 to 10,000 years ago
これは4000年から1万年前のことです
this warm climate
この温暖な気候
It is caused by itself to make the climate environment particularly good
それ自体が気候環境を特に良好にするために引き起こされる
why
なぜ
Because you speak purely for the warmth of the temperature
純粋に温度の温もりを語るから
You can go to lower latitudes to find warmer conditions
温暖な環境を求めて低緯度に行くこともできます
And all the four ancient civilizations developed almost in the middle and high latitudes
そして、4つの古代文明はすべてほぼ中緯度から高緯度で発展しました。
Not to mention the Huaxia people, we chose the Yellow River as the mother river of our so-called civilization
華夏族は言うまでもなく、私たちはいわゆる文明の母なる川として黄河を選びました。
If it is purely for warmth, it can choose the Yangtze River
純粋に暖かさだけを求めるなら長江を選ぶこともできる
The Yangtze River is more abundant
長江のほうが水量が多い
So it did not choose the Yangtze River
だから長江を選ばなかった
It means that warmth is definitely not the first consideration
つまり、暖かさは決して第一の考慮事項ではないということです
Elsewhere we also think warmth isn't really a first consideration
他の地域では、暖かさは実際には第一の考慮事項ではないと考えています
The reason I mentioned just now is that Lucy
先ほど言った理由は、ルーシーです。
Lucy to people for 3 million years
ルーシーは300万年間人々に伝えました
evolutionary life of man
人間の進化の人生
basically living on an earth that is one degree colder than it is now
基本的に今より1度寒い地球に住んでいます
Because we have long been accustomed to this cool climate
私たちはこの涼しい気候に長年慣れているので、
another one
もう一つ
another very important point
もう一つの非常に重要な点
That is to say, let's look at the cool climate
つまり、涼しい気候を見てみましょう
what does it mean
どういう意味ですか
The cool climate environment actually includes a wide range of
冷涼な気候環境には、実際にはさまざまな環境が含まれます。
it actually i think
それは実際に私が思う
The most important point is to include natural disasters which are relatively rare
最も重要な点は、比較的まれな自然災害を含めることです。
When natural disasters are less likely to occur
自然災害が起こりにくい時期
Only then can it be called a cool climate environment
そうしてこそ冷涼な気候環境と言えるのです
Everyone assumes to look a little more carefully
誰もがもう少し注意深く見ようと思う
The geographic location of the four major civilizations and five ancient countries
四大文明と古代五国の地理的位置
you all noticed
皆さんは気づきましたか
No country is right next to the sea
海のすぐ隣に国はない
And no country is right next to the earthquake zone
そして地震地帯のすぐ隣にある国はない
According to the earthquake zone, the closest one is probably China.
地震地帯によると、最も近いのはおそらく中国です。
It's pretty close according to Japan
日本からするとかなり近いですね
But wait a while and see that the low tide of raising young people is still far from the sea.
しかし、若者を育てる干潮はまだ海から遠いことが分かるまで待ってください。
So the so-called earthquakes and tsunamis had no effect on these ancient civilizations
つまり、いわゆる地震と津波はこれらの古代文明に影響を与えませんでした。
But I'm afraid it's also those ancient civilizations that are really influenced by ancient civilizations.
しかし、実際に古代文明の影響を受けているのは、その古代文明でもあるのではないかと思います。
Those close to earthquakes and tsunamis may not have developed
地震や津波に近いものは発達していない可能性がある
I believe
私は信じている
The problem now is that the risk of natural disasters is relatively low
現在の問題は、自然災害のリスクが比較的低いことです
Floods and droughts I believe are our ancestors
洪水と干ばつは私たちの祖先だと思います
and any of their people from ancient civilizations
そして古代文明の人々
What they worry about most should be the thing they worry about most
彼らが最も心配していることは、彼らが最も心配していることであるはずです
flood
洪水
with the drought
干ばつとともに
Actually until now
実は今まで
Chinese mainland
中国本土
Speaking of which, of course we are in Taiwan.
そういえば、ここはもちろん台湾です。
We in Taiwan are all worried about floods
私たち台湾人は皆洪水を心配しています
best every year
毎年最高の
The most shocking is the flood
最も衝撃的なのは洪水です
But in mainland China it is a drought
しかし中国本土では干ばつが発生している
Economic losses from their drought yearly drought
毎年の干ばつによる経済的損失
it's a disaster for them
それは彼らにとって災難だ
i remember the number
番号は覚えています
It is almost like this in more than 70% of their natural disasters every year
毎年発生する自然災害の 70% 以上がほぼ同様です
so
それで
How to avoid floods and droughts is actually the most important issue
洪水や干ばつをどう回避するかが実は最も重要な問題だ
Let's take China as an example below
以下に中国を例に挙げてみましょう
that
それか
Yangshao culture is famous
揚韶文化が有名
he is about a.d.
彼は西暦くらいです。
three thousand five thousand years ago
三千五千年前
Yang Shao Culture
楊紹文化
Did you see
あなたは見ましたか
It's quite far away
かなり遠いです
I'm afraid the tsunami won't reach here
ここまで津波は来ないと思う
This is near the Yellow River
ここは黄河の近くです
OK
OK
Of course it was 3,000 to 5,000 years ago
もちろん3000～5000年前の話です
more than a thousand years later
千年以上後
to the downward position
下の位置
is here
ここにある
Of course, I didn't want to post this picture.
もちろん、この写真を掲載するつもりはありませんでした。
when i put it in
私がそれを入れたとき
Originally, President Wang Fu was not here to preside over the
元々、王福総統はこの会議を主宰するためにここに来たわけではない。
So I boldly put it in
なので思い切って入れてみました
After he came
彼が来た後
I have sent it to Mr. Hou
侯さんに送りました。
too late to withdraw
撤退するには遅すぎる
I know this picture is still a bit worse than his picture standard
この写真が彼の写真の標準よりもまだ少し悪いのはわかっています
But there are a lot of interesting things in this picture
しかし、この写真には興味深いものがたくさんあります
did you notice
気づきましたか
not just down toward him is in this totally in
彼に向かってだけではなく、完全にこの中にいます
Yellow River Basin
黄河流域
it
それ
Here is the Yellow River
ここが黄河です
it is the modern yellow river
それは現代の黄河です
did you notice
気づきましたか
The Yellow River and the Yangtze River are very different
黄河と長江は大きく異なります
Yangtze
長江
look
見て
messy little nearby
近くにある散らかった小さなもの
look small lake
小さな湖を見てください
They are actually big lakes
実は大きな湖なんです
You see the Yellow River is naked
黄河が裸であることがわかります
not a single lake
湖はひとつもない
it's interesting
それは面白い
until the Qin Dynasty
秦の時代までは
This neighbor of the Qin Dynasty
この秦王朝の隣人
Everyone noticed that the Yellow River is still the main
黄河が依然として本流であることに誰もが気づきました
the yellow river is here
黄河はここにあります
OK
OK
this way
こちらです
Or the Yellow River
あるいは黄河
Yangtze river in
長江
OK
OK
The Yangtze River has just begun to develop
長江は発展を始めたばかり
It's Qin Dynasty
秦王朝ですよ
So from just now BC
それで、今からBC
five thousand years to now
今から5千年後
almost five thousand years
ほぼ五千年
Chinese culture has always been
中国文化は常に
Mainly the Yellow River
主に黄河
But with the Yellow River as the center
しかし、黄河を中心として
See how the Yellow River treats the Chinese nation
黄河が中華民族をどのように扱っているかを見る
Guide County near Qinghai
青海省近郊のガイド県
If people don't write this as the Yellow River
もし人々がこれを黄河と書かなかったら
No matter how I guess, I can't guess that this is the Yellow River
どう考えてもここが黄河とは思えない
Because you see the river is quite clear
川がとても澄んでいるのが見えるから
It feels like swimming in summer
夏に泳いでいるような気分です
must be very enjoyable
とても楽しいはずです
But here is Qinghai
しかしここは青海省です
200 kilometers downstream of it
その200キロ下流
It's Lanzhou
蘭州です
Yellow River in Lanzhou
蘭州の黄河
You see it's yellow
黄色いのがわかりますか
we can see how far it is
どれくらい離れているかがわかります
The picture of Qinghai is almost here on this machine
青海の写真はもうすぐこのマシンに登場します
there here
ここにあります
The blue continent is a little bit above the red dot
青い大陸は赤い点の少し上にあります
So basically only the difference
基本的には違いだけです
About two or three hundred kilometers vary
約200～300キロメートルは変動します
So from the clear is
それで、クリアからは
How do you say that is very clean
それはとてもきれいだとどう思いますか
Do it right away, that is to say
すぐにやれ、つまり
I'm totally loess in it
私はそれに完全に負けています
Well, we also have good statistics on this now.
さて、これに関しては現在、良い統計も得られています。
Of course the Yellow River belongs to the Republic of China as we know it now
もちろん、今私たちが知っているように、黄河は中華民国に属します
The Mother of Chinese Culture in the Republic of China and
中華民国における中国文化の母、そして
That park was between 5,000 and 2,000 years ago
その公園は5,000年から2,000年前にあった
This has always been here
これはいつもここにありました
Actually we just saw
実際、私たちはちょうど見たばかりです
In fact, until the park
実はこの公園まで
When talking about the Warring States Period
戦国時代を語るとき
In the future, the Yellow River will still dominate
将来的にも黄河が主流になるでしょう
for the main place
メインの場所に
as a center
センターとして
But we know the historical record
しかし、私たちは歴史的な記録を知っています
Over the past 2,500 years or so
過去2,500年ほどにわたって
flooding of the yellow river
黄河の氾濫
almost 1600 times
約1600回
Average 1.6 years
平均1.6年
flood once
一度洪水する
i think everyone knows
誰もが知っていると思います
Bo Yang
ボー・ヤン
Bo Yang just said
ボー・ヤンがさっき言った
The Yellow River is like a bird on the ground
黄河は地上の鳥のようだ
writhing beautiful
のたうち回る美しい
dragon
ドラゴン
Bring us an irresistible disaster
私たちに抗えない災いをもたらす
If the Yellow River says
黄河が言うなら
really is
本当にそうです
like this
このような
i can't figure it out
理解できません
Ancestors of Huaxia
華夏の祖先
how would you think
どう思いますか
ran to the edge of the Yellow River
黄河のほとりまで走った
to develop that culture
その文化を発展させるために
I think
私が思うに
he this
彼はこれ
IQ even me
IQは私でも
Of course, people's IQ has always been
もちろん、人々のIQは常に
enhanced
強化された
For example, here my IQ
たとえば、ここで私のIQは
should be relatively low
比較的低いはずです
Because everyone looks younger than me
みんな私より若く見えるから
The younger generations are indeed
若い世代は確かに
This IQ has been increasing
このIQは上がっています
but our
しかし私たちの
Chinese ancestors
中国の祖先
No matter how low your IQ is, it won't be that low.
いくらIQが低くてもそこまで低いわけではありません。
Let's say there is a big flood every year and a half
1年半ごとに大洪水が起こるとしましょう
you are still there
あなたはまだそこにいる
develop your culture
自分の文化を発展させる
This is very, very unreasonable
これは非常に非常に不合理です
so i thought
ので、私は考えました
When I was speaking this time, I thought
今回話していて思ったのですが、
I want to discuss this issue with you.
この問題についてあなたと話し合いたいと思います。
look
見て
We saw
私たちは見た
That is to say, the Yellow River was long ago
つまり、黄河は昔からあったということです。
5000 BC 2000 years ago
2000年前の紀元前5000年
temperature we see
私たちが見る温度
2 degrees C beyond the present
現在より 2 ℃
This is absolutely proven
これは完全に証明されてるよ
over there
そちら側
That is to say, digging out
つまり掘り出すということです
have dug this fish
この魚を掘った
have dug this rhino
このサイを掘りました
These are more tropical animals.
これらはより熱帯の動物です
So the temperature at that time
それでその時の気温は
The guess should be the guess should be no problem
推測は推測であって問題ないはず
The loess soil was originally very fertile.
黄土はもともと非常に肥沃な土壌でした。
easy to do
簡単にできる
So at that time, there were actually many, many
ですから当時は、実際にはたくさんの人がいたのです。
favorable conditions
有利な条件
In addition, they mentioned that there is a saying in this ancient book
さらに、この古書にはこんな格言があるとのこと。
There are many large lakes in the middle and lower reaches of the Yellow River
黄河の中下流には大きな湖がたくさんあります。
Just now I told you that there is no lake now
さっきみんなに言ったんだけど、今は湖はないって
At that time many great lakes
当時、多くの大きな湖があった
Let's just say that the existence of the Great Lakes proves that
五大湖の存在がそれを証明しているとだけ言っておきましょう。
The Yellow River carries very little sediment
黄河には土砂がほとんど流れていない
If there is a lot of sand
砂が多い場合
as now
今のように
any kind of lake
どんな種類の湖でも
will be pre-qualified in a few years
数年以内に事前資格が得られるだろう
So it shows that I was super late for this sentence at that time.
つまり、当時私がこの文章に超遅刻したことを示しています。
He said it showed that there was less rainstorm at that time
当時は暴風雨が少なかったことを示していると彼は述べた
I said I've been raining for so long
長い間雨が降っていると言いました
How dare someone tell me
誰かが私に言うなんて
At that time the rainstorm was small
その時の暴風雨は小さかった
so it's very difficult
だからとても難しいです
But his guess is very reasonable.
しかし、彼の推測は非常に合理的です。
Because at that time since there was very little sediment
当時は土砂がほとんどなかったので、
His torrential rain should be rare
彼の豪雨は稀なはずだ
Forest and grassland are all in good condition
森林も草地も良好な状態です
That is to say at that time
つまりあの時は
I guess the Yellow River is clear
黄河は澄んでる気がする
Of course when I write this clearly
もちろんこれをはっきり書くと
This is also far
これも遠い
I know that our Vice President Wang is going to host
私たちの王副大統領が主催することを知っています
So I don't know if he will say later
だから彼が後で言うかどうかは分からない
You have a problem with this
これには問題があります
But this thing
でも、このことは
I believe this my past ah
これが私の過去だと信じています ああ
Actually, it was actually when the Five Brothers of the Han Dynasty
実はそれは漢の五兄弟の時代でした。
That that was already in AD there
それはすでにADにあったこと
After AD, it is written in the whole article.
AD以降、記事全体にそのことが書かれていました。
He doesn't have the name Huang He
彼には黄鶴という名前はありません
And the river at that time was the Yellow River at that time
そしてその時の川は黄河でした
Collectively called the river, not the Yellow River
黄河ではなく、総称して川と呼ばれます
So it is likely that even when performing
そのため、パフォーマンスを行っている場合でも、
This Yellow River may be a little yellow
この黄河は少し黄色かもしれません
But definitely not as yellow as today
でも、今日ほど黄色くないのは確かです
OK
OK
So this seems to make sense
これには意味があるように思えます
except this
これを除いて
We actually had a recent
実は最近、
Ours is also why I put this
私たちもこれを置いた理由です
The reason this little history is here
この小さな歴史がここにある理由
Some of our recent research
私たちの最近の研究の一部
sorry
ごめん
I must have been pressing this thing
きっとこれを押していたんだろう
it doesn't work
それは機能しません
back to the original
元に戻る
We did a recent study
私たちは最近の研究を行いました
That is to say, when the sea temperature in the tropics is relatively low,
つまり、熱帯地方の海水温が比較的低いときは、
in this case
この場合
Global rainfall intensity will decrease
世界的な降雨量は減少する
That is to say, the rainstorm will decrease
つまり、暴風雨は減少します
And light rain is relatively less
小雨も比較的少ないです
in this case
この場合
It will provide more favorable rainfall conditions for Nongmu
農武にとってより好ましい降雨条件が提供されるでしょう
This is an estimate we made
これは私たちが行った見積もりです
what does this picture represent
この絵は何を表していますか
That is, we calculate the rainfall intensity
つまり、降雨強度を計算します
With low pseudo-degrees is the change in tropical ocean temperature
低い擬似度では、熱帯の海洋温度が変化します
The intensity of the rainfall is here
雨の強さはここにあります
Divide the global rainfall into 10 equal parts
地球の降雨量を 10 等分します
The strongest rainfall is here
最も強い雨がここにあります
Minimal rainfall is here
最小限の降雨量がここにあります
That 10 is the top 10% of heavy rainfall
その 10 は豪雨の上位 10% です
Did you see
あなたは見ましたか
If you increase the sea temperature by one degree
海水温を1度上げると
Its heavy rainfall will increase by almost 100%
大雨はほぼ100%増加するでしょう
You think the sea temperature at that time was cooler
当時の海水温はもっと冷たかったと思います
if it's cold
寒かったら
In other words, the heavy rainfall should be smaller than the current
つまり、大雨は現在よりも少ないはずです。
almost double
ほぼ2倍
This means that at that time in the Yellow River Basin
ということは、当時黄河流域では
The rain at that time was the kind of torrential rain.
その時の雨は豪雨のようなものでした。
much less than now
今よりずっと少ない
but light rain
でも小雨
light rain it will increase if it is cold
小雨 寒ければ増えるでしょう
Here is the temperature increase it decreases
ここでは温度が上昇し、低下します
it increases when it is cold
寒いと増える
Moderate rain will increase
適度な雨が多くなるでしょう
So we all know that heavy rain is of course related to floods and landslides
したがって、大雨が洪水や地滑りに当然関連していることは誰もが知っています。
So you reduce the risk of this flood
したがって、この洪水のリスクを軽減できます
Moderate rain increases
中程度の雨が増加
Moderate rain is an important moisture to keep the soil moist
適度な雨は土壌の湿り気を保つために重要な水分です
It is also an important oxygen-containing edge for groundwater
また、地下水にとって重要な酸素を含むエッジでもあります。
Therefore, the increase of light rain can reduce sweating in
したがって、小雨が増加すると、発汗が減少する可能性があります。
And it is very beneficial to the maintenance of deep drench and straight back
そして、それは深い溝とまっすぐな背中の維持に非常に有益です
I make a picture here
ここで絵を描きます
Basically, it means that the tropical sea temperature is low
基本的に熱帯の海水温が低いことを意味します
The intensity of the rainfall will decrease
雨の強さは弱まるでしょう
Light rain will increase, heavy rain will decrease
小雨が増え、大雨が減る
Of course, to use an old saying, it means good weather
もちろん、古いことわざを使えば、それは良い天気を意味します
in this case
この場合
The existence of creatures and lakes becomes possible
生き物や湖の存在が可能になる
That is to say, the Yellow River was not yellow at that time.
つまり、当時の黄河は黄色ではなかったのです。
Actually it makes sense
実はそれは理にかなっている
In terms of weather
天気に関しては
The temperature of the original ocean
元の海の温度
The ocean is cooler
海のほうが涼しいよ
OK Ocean temperatures at lower latitudes are cooler
OK 低緯度の海水温は低い
this is a very important factor
これは非常に重要な要素です
We are thinking that reducing the intensity
強度を下げることを考えています
Then make soil and water conservation in the Yellow River Basin easier
そうすれば、黄河流域の土壌と水の保全が容易になります
That is to say, in the Yellow River Basin
つまり、黄河流域では
That is to say, during this period
つまり、この期間中、
Gongyuan from 2000 to 5000 years
2000年から5000年前の公元
we can know
私たちは知ることができます
this is fertile soil
ここは肥沃な土壌です
forest lake
森の湖
very many
非常に多くの
good weather
いい天気
Yellow River becomes very reliable
黄河は非常に信頼できるものになります
No
いいえ
Definitely not a flood every 1.6 years
1.6年ごとに洪水が起こるわけではない
I just said it
さっき言いました
The temperature is relatively mild
気温も比較的穏やかです
This will become the kiln basket of Chinese culture
これが中国文化の窯籠となる
will also
也会
that is
あれは
this is what i think
これが私が思うことです
Why was the Yellow River chosen as the mother river of Chinese culture?
なぜ黄河が中国文化の母なる川に選ばれたのでしょうか?
Here I mentioned heavy rain water control
ここで豪雨対策について触れました
That's what I'm talking about here
それが私がここで話していることです
I said
私は言いました
For example, in 2000 BC
たとえば、紀元前 2000 年には
Also every 1.6 years on average
また平均して 1.6 年ごと
Everyone
みんな
You can figure it out
あなたはそれを理解することができます
He cured the water for 13 years
他治水13年
did not come home three times
3回も帰ってこなかった
Did not go home three times
3回も帰らなかった
it is known
周知された
this 13 years
この13年
He should flood 8 times
彼は8回洪水するはずだ
ok
Ok
on basic statistics
基本的な統計について
that flooded 8 times
8回も浸水した
Think about it
考えてみてください
No matter how hard you rain
どんなに激しい雨が降っても
But of course he succeeded
しかし、もちろん彼は成功しました
he his father failed
彼は父親が失敗した
Everyone knows what the consequences are
その結果がどうなるかは誰もが知っています
then he succeeded
それから彼は成功した
Is it really raining in the past
昔は本当に雨が降っていたのか
It is really better than the past 2000
過去の2000年よりは本当に良くなった
Let's just say that the next 2500 years
次の2500年だとしましょう
The Yellow River floods all day long
黄河は一日中氾濫する
The Yellow River has this all day long
黄河は一日中こんな感じです
dedicated person
献身的な人
smart man engineer
賢い人エンジニア
to control the Yellow River
黄河を制圧するために
bad governance
悪い統治
and he
そして彼
You see heavy rain for 13 years
13年ぶりに大雨が降る
but all succeeded
しかし、すべて成功しました
so so i say
だから私は言います
This is Holland Green
こちらはホーランドグリーンです
I believe this is not true
これは真実ではないと思います
but i was guessing
でも私は推測していました
My answer is to say
私の答えはこう言います
Within 13 years of heavy rain and stagnant water
大雨と停滞水から13年以内
like we just said
先ほど言ったように
good weather basically
基本的に良い天気
Of course there are occasional small floods
もちろん小規模な洪水も時々発生します
maybe once or twice
おそらく1回か2回
that it this
それはこれです
and high technology
そしてハイテク
then try very hard
それから一生懸命頑張ってください
once or twice, of course
もちろん一度か二度
it passed
通りました
I also think it's the right time and place
私もそれが適切な時間と場所だと思います
all helped it
みんなが助けてくれた
Of course it won't work if it doesn't work hard
もちろん頑張らないとダメですよ
But the so-called heavy rain
しかし、いわゆる大雨
It should be mostly its luck
それはほとんど運のせいだろう
i'm guessing
私は推測します
instead of saying its 13 years
13年と言う代わりに
it's really governed so well
本当によく管理されている
suppose it's that powerful
それくらい強力だと思うよ
and it that method
そしてその方法です
I also know later
私も後から知りました
next 2500 years
次の2500年
that is to say those people
つまりあの人たち
such a smart person
とても賢い人
There should be a way
方法があるはずです
governance success
ガバナンスの成功
so i believe
だから私は信じます
From this logic
このロジックからすると
indeed in
確かに
that is
あれは
When ancient civilizations developed
古代文明が発展したとき
that
それか
at that time
その時
Climatic conditions
気候条件
That is to say, the conditions of rainfall
つまり、降水条件は
is far better than
よりもはるかに優れています
far than
よりもはるかに
that is
あれは
past
過去
over 2000 years
2000年以上
well done
素晴らしい
then finish the story
それから話を終わらせてください
everyone is fine
みんな元気だよ
here
ここ
because I can't wait
待ちきれないから
tell these historical things
これらの歴史的なことを伝える
if there is a problem
問題がある場合
can now bring it up
今すぐそれを取り上げることができます
Then we seem to have quite a long time today
それでは今日はかなり時間がありそうです
seems to be every time
毎回あるようです
ah
ああ
right
右
have a lot of time
時間がたくさんある
so everyone has a problem
だから誰もが問題を抱えている
mention at any time
いつでも言及
ah
ああ
i think this is very
これはとてもいいと思います
very interesting
とても興味深い
hear the story
話を聞く
that's in
それは入っています
The Yangtze River We know that the Yangtze River was 50 or 60 years ago
長江 長江が 50 ～ 60 年前にあったことはわかっています。
It was clear before
前から明らかだった
Clear and without yellow sand
透明で黄砂なし
but now
でも今
It's like turning into the Yellow River
黄河に変わったようだ
the main reason
主な理由
Of course it's because of the development
もちろん開発のせいです
Cut down the upper forest
上部の森を伐採する
and then developed a variety of uses
その後、さまざまな用途が開発されました
So resulting in the current
その結果、現在が
The Yangtze River is also changing
長江も変わりつつある
So this of course this could be
もちろんこれはそうかもしれません
because time is short
時間が短いので
this big change happened
この大きな変化が起こりました
Maybe it's not about the climate
もしかしたら気候のせいではないかもしれない
Then the change in the Yellow River changes from clear to yellow
すると黄河の流れが透明から黄色に変わります
Is it also because of the impact of development?
これも開発の影響でしょうか？
i think it's right
それが正しいと思います
That is to say, from clear to yellow
つまり、透明から黄色へ
It's not just natural reasons
自然な理由だけではありません
that natural cause i believe
その自然な原因を私は信じています
indeed there are
確かにあります
The climate is changing
気候は変化しています
OK
OK
The reason may be more important
理由の方が重要かもしれない
you talk
あなたは話します
Ask me if the Yellow River is really turning yellow because of man-made
黄河が本当に黄色くなっているのは人工のせいなのか尋ねてください
or natural reasons
または自然な理由
I believe that although I would like to have
私はそう思いますが、
However, there should be more human reasons
しかし、もっと人間的な理由があるはずです
Population after the Warring States Period
戦国時代以降の人口
not after the Warring States Period
戦国時代以降ではない
After the Qing Dynasty
清朝以降
The population is increasing very fast
人口は非常に急速に増加しています
Especially when the country begins to unify
特に国が統一され始めると
start getting bigger
大きくなり始める
growing population
人口の増加
Lin Kan speaks very, very fast
リン・カンはとてもとても早く話します
Soil and water conservation is more difficult
土壌と水の保全はさらに困難になる
but i can say
しかし、私は言うことができます
Even the Yellow River
黄河さえも
We're going back now to keep it hydrated
水分補給するために今戻ります
it can actually recover to
実際に回復できるのは
That is to say, the coverage of forest and grassland is everywhere.
つまり、森林と草原の範囲はどこにでもあります。
i actually have
私は実際に持っています
because of its climate now
今の気候のせいで
very unsuitable
非常に不適当
This is my forest and grassland
ここは私の森と草原です
that's my kind of coverage
それが私の取材方法です
yes no more questions yet
はい、まだ質問はありません
so no words
だから言葉は要らない
I think I will introduce to you
紹介していこうと思います
That means returning
つまり戻るということです
Back to the question we started to talk about today
今日話し始めた質問に戻ります
That is to say spring and autumn warming
つまり、春と秋の温暖化です。
Impact on Taiwan
台湾への影響
before speaking
話す前に
I thought I'd better introduce
紹介したほうがいいと思いました
What is the difference between weather and climate
天気と気候の違いは何ですか
because it is often misunderstood
よく誤解されるので
Look at the weather in general
天気全般を見てください
I am a more general definition
私はより一般的な定義です
In fact, there is no very strict definition
実は厳密な定義はありません
Generally the weather is
一般的に天気は
The short-term state and change of the air
短期的な状態と空気の変化
In the short term we generally
短期的には通常、
say within 10 days
10日以内に言ってください
Basically within 10 days
基本的に10日以内
why use 10 days
なぜ10日を使うのか
The main thing is that we now
重要なことは、私たちが今、
best weather forecaster
最高の気象予報士
Basically can only predict 10 days
基本的には10日間しか予測できません
10 days later
10日後
Talking about the weather is useless
天気の話をしても無駄だ
The weather you guessed, the weather he told
あなたが推測した天気、彼が言った天気
exactly the same
まったく同じ
It's all 50% right and 50% wrong
それはすべて50％正しくて、50％間違っています
so this we mean the weather
つまりこれは天気のことです
That example is what the temperature will be tomorrow
その例は明日の気温はどうなるかということです
The weather today is bad
今日は天気が悪いです
the climate is very different
気候はとても違います
Climate is the long-term average of weather
気候は天気の長期平均です
This long term has a certain definition
この長期には一定の定義があります
World Meteorological Organization definition
世界気象機関の定義
long term is 30 years
長期は30年
That means you have 30 years of data
つまり 30 年分のデータがあるということです
you are qualified to say
あなたには言う資格があります
I have a climate value for this
私はこれに対する気候の値を持っています
For example, if we say that the global average
たとえば、世界平均だとすると、
The temperature is 15 degrees
気温は15度です
That means we at least have a past
つまり、少なくとも過去があるということです
30 years of data
30年分のデータ
to average out this 15 degrees
この 15 度を平均するには
Of course we have hundreds of years of data
もちろん、私たちは何百年ものデータを持っています
How many typhoons come to Taiwan every year
台湾には毎年何本の台風が来ますか
We've certainly had good weather this year
確かに今年は良い天気に恵まれましたね
lucky only one
幸運なのは一人だけ
But does anyone know how many typhoons we have on average?
しかし、台風が平均してどれくらい発生するか知っている人はいますか?
does anyone have a guess
誰か推測がありますか
alone air does not count
空気だけではカウントされない
seven
セブン
no one has to guess
誰も推測する必要はありません
We have an average of four typhoons a year
年間平均4回の台風が発生します
Qingtai
青台
There is also a definition
という定義もあります
What is typhoon Qingtai?
台風「青台」とは何ですか？
The Bureau of Meteorology issued a warning on the road.
気象庁は道路上に警報を発令した。
Even before it arrived in Taiwan
台湾に到着する前から
It's okay to turn a corner and walk away
角を曲がって歩き去っても大丈夫です
continue
続く
you are not there yet
あなたはまだそこにいません
Won't
しません
I you are moving
私はあなたが動いています
it's gonna be the last chance
それが最後のチャンスになるだろう
There are almost four a year
年に4本くらいあるよ
We only have one this year
今年は1つだけです
it was better for us then
そのときの方が私たちにとって良かった
and additionally
そしてさらに
typhoon four typhoon
台風4号
An average of four typhoons a year
台風は年間平均4回発生
It brings us almost 40 percent of our rainfall
降水量のほぼ 40 パーセントをもたらします。
So if you say that it is a good thing that the typhoon does not come
だから台風が来なくて良かったと言うなら
that's totally wrong
それは完全に間違っています
It's a bad thing if the typhoon doesn't come
台風が来ないと大変だ
If none of the four typhoons comes
4つの台風が一つも来なかったら
Forty percent of our annual rain is gone
年間の雨の 40 パーセントが消えてしまった
60% left
残り60%
The second year of spring plowing guarantees that you can do nothing
春の耕作の2年目は何もできないことを保証する
In fact, this year we can say that luck is the best.
実際、今年は運が一番良いと言えます。
Several typhoons are coming
いくつかの台風が近づいています
just wipe it on the side
側面を拭くだけ
bring us a lot of rain
私たちにたくさんの雨を降らせてください
I still remember when the first typhoon came
最初の台風が来たときのことを今でも覚えています
Seems like we were heading for a drought
どうやら干ばつに向かっているようだ
Then there is a typhoon coming
そしたら台風が来てるよ
become rainy
雨が降る
There are several typhoons this year
今年は台風が多いですね
that said it brought the rain
それは雨を降らせたと言った
But it didn't bring anything special, just more rain
でも特別なことは何も起こらず、ただ雨が降っただけだった
Of course there will be disasters
もちろん災害も起こるだろう
After we make this definition
この定義をした後
Many questions we can understand very quickly
多くの質問はすぐに理解できます
because the media often say
メディアがよく言うから
Just like there were several weather events in previous winters
前の冬にいくつかの気象現象があったように
very heavy snow and cold
とても大雪で寒い
Then some media said
すると、一部のメディアがこう言いました。
Are we going into Xiaoice and Qi?
XiaoiceとQiに行くのでしょうか？
Everyone knows this definition
誰もがこの定義を知っています
Xiaobing and the flag are hundreds of years old
小兵と国旗は数百年前のものです
one or two hundred years
100年か200年
its a climate event
それは気候変動です
This is a few weather events
これはいくつかの気象現象です
two are not the same
二つは同じではありません
So of course it doesn't mean
だからもちろんそういう意味ではない
In addition, this particular event
さらに、今回の特別イベントは、
Morakot European heatwave
モラコットヨーロッパの熱波
Said to be caused by climate warming
気候温暖化が原因と言われている
Why
なぜ
Because this is still a few weather events
まだ気象現象が少ないので
And climate warming is a climate problem
そして気候温暖化は気候問題です
Even without climate warming
気候温暖化がなくても
We also know that typhoons like Morakot
また、モラコットのような台風が発生することもわかっています。
There is still a chance to come to Taiwan
台湾に来るチャンスはまだあります
not no
いいえではありません
OK
OK
africa europe heatwave
アフリカ ヨーロッパ 熱波
There is also a chance
チャンスもあるよ
it's not without
ないわけではない
but what can we say
しかし、何と言えますか
in the context of climate warming
気候温暖化の文脈で
I'll show you here
ここでお見せします
We used to be in Taiwan
私たちは台湾によく行っていました
Analyze data from 1961 to 2005
1961 年から 2005 年までのデータを分析
Do an average every 10 years
10年ごとに平均を計算する
Then do an analysis of rainfall intensity
次に降雨強度の分析を行います
here is heavy rain
ここは大雨です
This is cat cat rain
これは猫猫雨です
OK
OK
On average, people can see different colors every ten years
平均すると、人は 10 年ごとに異なる色に見えるようになります
The most recent is only five years
一番最近のものはたったの5年です
2001 to 2005
2001年から2005年まで
You can see that heavy rainfall is increasing
豪雨が増えているのがわかります
With the age because it is getting hotter
年々暑くなるにつれて
OK increases with temperature
OKは温度とともに増加します
While light rain decreases with temperature
小雨は気温とともに弱まるものの、
very obvious
非常に明白な
For Typhoon Morakot
台風モラコットについて
This picture makes sense
この写真には意味がある
Everyone noticed that the average rainfall in Morakot
誰もがモラコットの平均降水量に気づきました
It's about 40 mm per hour
1時間あたり約40mmです
40 kilometers
40キロ
40 kilometers per hour
時速40キロメートル
rain like this
こんな雨が降る
Between 1961 and 1970
1961 年から 1970 年の間
You see, it is almost equal to non-existence
ほら、それは存在しないに等しい
But after 45 years
しかし45年経つと
You can see that it has increased by almost
ほぼ増加していることがわかります
at least three times
少なくとも3回は
then you can
そうすればできます
so to speak
いわば
Of course, what I'm talking about now is more general.
もちろん、私が今話していることはより一般的なものです。
That is to say
つまり
Morakot
モラコット
rain like this typhoon Morakot
今回の台風モラコットのような雨が降る
now than before
以前よりも今
Its thirst rate increased
喉の渇きの速度が増加しました
and increased considerably
そしてかなり増えた
possibly several times
おそらく数回
So from this point of view
したがって、この観点からすると
we can talk
私たちは話すことができる
That is, this single event
つまり、この一つの出来事は、
relationship with climate warming
気候温暖化との関係
Speaking of climate warming, of course
気候温暖化といえば、もちろん
We still have to introduce the greenhouse effect
私たちはまだ温室効果を導入する必要があります
greenhouse effect
温室効果
The most obvious greenhouse effect
最も明白な温室効果
that is
あれは
If there were no greenhouse gases
温室効果ガスがなかったら
average temperature of our planet
私たちの地球の平均気温
It should be minus 19 degrees
マイナス19度くらいあるはず
It is easy to calculate it with the formula of physics
物理の公式で計算するのは簡単です
but we are now
でも私たちは今
just now we saw
今私たちは見ました
The global average temperature is 15 degrees
地球の平均気温は15度
So the greenhouse gas greenhouse effect
つまり、温室効果ガスの温室効果
gives us 34 degrees
34度になります
that is
あれは
very high temperature
非常に高い温度
The main greenhouse gases of the earth are as follows:
地球上の主な温室効果ガスは次のとおりです。
Among them, what everyone often hears is Jiawan, which loves to raise carbon dioxide.
その中でも皆さんがよく耳にするのが、二酸化炭素を上げるのが大好きなジアワンです。
less commonly heard is water vapor
あまり一般的には聞かれないが水蒸気
Water vapor is actually one of the most important greenhouse gases
水蒸気は実際には最も重要な温室効果ガスの 1 つです
It says it's inside 34 degrees
気温は34度だそうです
its very rough estimate
非常に大まかな見積もり
it accounts for at least half
少なくとも半分を占めています
It occupies half because of water
半分は水分で占められています
water vapor relationship
水蒸気の関係
Others are relatively few
他は比較的少ない
But why don't we hear the water
でもなぜ水の音が聞こえないのでしょう
Because mainly water is not affected by water in the air
主に水は空気中の水分の影響を受けないため
unaffected by human activities
人間の活動の影響を受けない
so we got lucky
それで私たちは幸運でした
water untouched by us
私たちが触れていない水
If it is really influenced by us
それが本当に私たちに影響されているのなら
that's really
それは本当に
it's a big deal
それは大したことだ
But these other
しかし、これらの他の
Ozone
オゾン
effector
エフェクター
are all affected by human activities
すべては人間の活動の影響を受ける
and have now increased a lot
そして今ではかなり増えています
Especially the armor pill increased
特にアーマーピルが増えた
I'm afraid there are three times
残念ながら3回あります
tripled
3倍になった
The others are also adding considerable numbers
他の人もかなりの数を追加しています
we can see here
ここで見ることができます
You see when Komaru starts here
小丸がここから始まるのがわかります
Kamaru is here
カマルはここにいます
It was only less than 600
600未満だった
How much has it increased now
今はどれくらい増えましたか
almost 2000
ほぼ2000年
nearly quadrupled
ほぼ4倍に
dark carbon dioxide increase
暗黒二酸化炭素の増加
are also very obvious
も非常に明白です
effector increased significantly
エフェクターが大幅に増加
This is the year 2000
これは 2000 年です
this
これ
right
右
This is web recovery
これはウェブリカバリです
Push is 2000 years ago is here
2000年前のプッシュがここにある
Of course everyone will say
もちろん誰もが言うだろう
we have everything to cool now
今は冷やすものがすべて揃っています
How did this get cold?
これはどうして寒くなったのでしょうか？
Does anyone know this
これを知っている人はいますか
no one dozed off
誰も居眠りしなかった
so i ask the question
だから私は質問します
smile is not big
笑顔は大きくない
sometimes someone dozes off
時々誰かが居眠りする
I asked him
彼に聞いた
he woke up immediately
彼はすぐに目を覚ました
this is very effective
これはとても効果的です
Everyone seems to be paying attention today
今日はみんな注目しているようです
this thing like this currently
これは現在このようなものです
In fact, it is also a method that has only recently begun to be discovered.
実は、最近になって発見され始めた方法でもあります。
I remember it was in the 70s that I started to know how to cool
私が涼しさを知り始めたのは 70 年代だったと記憶しています
That is to say, the Greenland or Antarctic
つまり、グリーンランドか南極です。
his ice
彼の氷
Hit one to knock down that icicle
一撃で氷柱を倒す
call up
電話をかける
Drill down and pull that icicle out
ドリルダウンしてつららを引き抜く
its icicles
そのつらら
Especially the icicles in Antarctica
特に南極のつらら
Antarctic snowfall is very slow
南極の降雪量は非常に遅い
Icicles are formed from what would have been snow
つららは雪だったものから形成されます
The snow pressure of snow pressure will be there in the future
雪圧の雪圧はこれからもあるだろう
crushed into ice
氷に砕かれた
OK
OK
when pressed into ice
氷に押し込まれると
Everyone knows that between snow and snow
雪と雪の間のことは誰もが知っています
it has bubbles
気泡が入っている
that bubble it is preserved
その泡は保存されています
that little bubble
その小さな泡
ice bubbles
氷の泡
you are deeper
あなたはもっと深いです
Of course the longer the history
もちろん歴史が長ければ長いほど
You take those air bubbles out of the ice
氷から気泡を取り除くと
take the air bubbles out
気泡を取り除く
There are bubbles in there
そこに気泡が入っている
Carbon dioxide can cool down
二酸化炭素は冷やすことができる
That's carbon dioxide
それは二酸化炭素です
Now we can put this
これで、これを置くことができます
Just say ice core
アイスコアって言ってみろよ
This can always be done
これはいつでも実行できます
Almost almost a million years ago
ほぼ100万年前
already
すでに
so say
だから、言って
Of course, only about
もちろん、ほんの約ですが、
400,000 years around 500,000 years
40万年 50万年左右
But there is hope to see
しかし、見られる希望はある
How much carbonized carbon was there 1 million years ago
100万年前にはどれくらいの炭素が炭化していましたか
The effect of greenhouse gases on the temperature of the world
温室効果ガスが世界の気温に及ぼす影響
The most obvious and best example is this graph
最も明白で最良の例はこのグラフです
OK this picture is also currently
OK、この写真も現在です
just say
言うだけ
Speaking of the current temperature increase
最近の気温上昇について言えば
Mainly man-made greenhouse gases
主に人為的な温室効果ガス
the result of the greenhouse effect of that effect
その効果の温室効果の結果
most important one argument
最も重要な 1 つの引数
what is this
これは何ですか
The black line represents
黒い線が表すのは、
Past observed temperature global
過去に観測された地球規模の気温
average change in temperature
平均気温変化
What about the blue line?
青い線はどうでしょうか？
The blue one is not a line
青いのは線ではありません
What about the blue one?
青いものはどうですか？
It means using this climate model
この気候モデルを使用することを意味します
take this increase in greenhouse gases
この温室効果ガスの増加を考えてみましょう
It is entirely assumed that there is no increase
増加しないことが完全に想定されています
Greenhouse gas assumptions have not changed at all
温室効果ガスの想定はまったく変わっていない
calculated global temperature
計算された地球の気温
What about the purple one?
紫のはどうでしょうか？
That is to say, the increase of this greenhouse gas
つまり、この温室効果ガスの増加は、
it's that influence put in
それはその影響力が与えられたものです
The results obtained
得られた結果
everyone can see
誰もが見ることができます
observed temperature
観測温度
is related to this greenhouse gas
この温室効果ガスに関係しています
This degree of mildness is quite high
このマイルド度はかなり高いです
Of course everyone also noticed
もちろんみんなも気づいてた
Here's something that doesn't match
ここに一致しないものがあります
Doesn't match any pattern
どのパターンにも一致しない
That means
つまり、
our climate change
私たちの気候変動
Although speaking now
今話しても
Efforts over the past few decades have made great progress
過去数十年にわたる取り組みは大きな進歩を遂げた
But there are still some places we don't know very well
でも、まだよくわかっていない場所もあります
What is the real reason for the temperature change
気温変化の本当の理由は何ですか
It is still a point of contention that everyone pays attention to.
それは今でも誰もが注目している論点です。
This graph is for the most important climate changes observed in the past
このグラフは、過去に観測された最も重要な気候変動に関するものです
As a result, it is always a relatively small section.
結果として、それは常に比較的小さなセクションになります。
The temperature change just above
直上での気温の変化
Temperature changes from the beginning of the thermometer almost 1850
1850年近くの温度計の始まりからの温度変化
still have a thermometer
まだ体温計がある
This is the increase in global temperature
これが地球の気温の上昇です
The thing I just talked about is here
今話したことはここにあります
The second graph is sea level rise
2番目のグラフは海面上昇です
Sea-level rise
海面上昇
This rising 100-year phenomenon
この上昇する100年現象
Let's say linear from 1900 to 2000
1900 年から 2000 年までの線形としましょう
The value is almost 0.6 degrees
値はほぼ0.6度です
If you use linear to measure sea level
リニアを使用して海面を測定する場合
Its increase is almost 15 cm
その増加は約15cmです
15 cm is not very high
15cmってそんなに高くないよ
actually
実際
This image shows snow cover in the northern hemisphere
この画像は北半球の積雪を示しています
Let's talk about this when we have time
時間があるときにこのことについて話しましょう
Although this is more time today
今日はもう時間あるけど
Or let me see when I speak at 7 o'clock
それとも7時に話すときに見せてください
It's almost 50 minutes now
もう50分近くあるよ
ah i remember
ああ、覚えています
supposedly 90 minutes
おそらく90分
within 90 minutes
90分以内
OK, 40 minutes left
残り40分
ah
ああ
Just now
ちょうど今
we see the temperature increase
気温が上昇しているのがわかります
is here
ここにある
That is to say, the part with the red line
つまり赤線の部分です
ok
Ok
Set it here
ここにセットする
This picture is from the past 2000 years
この写真は過去2000年のものです
Ours is now in 2000
私たちのものは現在2000年です
That means 11 years ago here in 2000
ということは、11年前の2000年ということになります。
The average global temperature over the past 1000 years
過去1000年間の地球の平均気温
picture of
の写真
ok, the part with red line means we have
OK、赤い線の部分は、
There are real instruments to measure the results
結果を測定するための実際の機器があります
I just saw what you saw
あなたが見たものを私も見ただけです
just now everyone saw
たった今みんなが見た
Make this and that coordinate very large
あれやこれやの座標を非常に大きくする
That coordinates are squeezed here
ここに座標が詰め込まれていること
You see 1900 is here
1900年がここにあるのがわかりますか
that is here
それはここです
The pattern I just talked about
さっき言ったパターン
There's no way to grind your little feet up here
ここであなたの小さな足を磨く方法はありません
ok
Ok
So this is the red part is modern
これが赤い部分が現代です
that front
その前
Almost 900 years have been made by other methods
900年近くも他の方法で作られてきた
these other ways to get out
他の脱出方法も
I believe
私は信じている
I don't want to ask
聞きたくない
Does anyone know of any other methods that are most commonly used
最も一般的に使用されている他の方法を知っている人はいますか
Other methods most commonly used
最も一般的に使用されるその他の方法
In fact, we have a lot of them in Taiwan.
実は台湾にもたくさんあるんです。
That is to say, there is a lot of information
つまり情報量が多いのです
But I haven't entered the picture yet.
でもまだ絵の中に入ってないんです。
That is to say, the annual rings of the tree
つまり、木の年輪です。
Tree rings are a very important
年輪はとても大切なものです
can be used for you to see we also know a lot about trees
私たちが木についてもよく知っていることを確認するために使用できます
Trees in Taiwan are thousands of years old
台湾の木は樹齢数千年
So the tree rings give us a lot of data
木の年輪は私たちに多くのデータを与えてくれます
In addition, of course the refrigerator I just mentioned
もちろん先ほどの冷蔵庫も
It is the kind of data for higher latitudes
高緯度のデータです
In addition there are some data
さらにいくつかのデータがあります
actually use this rock
実際にこの石を使ってみる
Rock because it conducts heat very slowly
熱の伝導が非常に遅いため、岩石になります。
after you drill it down
ドリルダウンした後
its past temperature
過去の温度
temperature at the depth of the rock
岩の深さの温度
It can be obtained from the previous temperature
前回の温度から取得可能
So here are some so-called alternative materials
そこで、いわゆる代替材料をいくつか紹介します。
made out of
から作られた
You can also see the uncertainty of modern times
現代の不確実性も見えてきます
gray part
灰色の部分
The gray part gets bigger the farther you go
灰色の部分が奥に行くほど大きくなります
The greater the uncertainty
不確実性が大きければ大きいほど
But you can also notice
しかし、気づくこともできます
This thing still looks pretty sophisticated
これはまだかなり洗練されているように見えます
because you look at 0.5 degrees
0.5度を見ているから
is so big
とても大きいです
So this looks pretty useful
これはかなり便利そうです
correct
正しい
But of course this means
しかし、もちろんこれはつまり、
Said to say the past
過去を言うと言った
one thousand years
一千年
The temperature basically does not change much
基本的に気温はあまり変わりません
Although a little less
少し少ないですが
But this reduced value
しかし、この減少した価値は
Just around 0.1 0.2 degrees
ちょうど0.1～0.2度くらい
And this 100 years
そしてこの100年
Suddenly increased by 0.6 degrees
一気に0.6度上昇
So this shows more
これでさらに表示されます
In other words, the unusualness of this temperature increase
つまり、この気温上昇の異常さは、
That also means that it is more likely
ということはその可能性が高いということでもあります
most likely caused by human activities
おそらく人間の活動が原因である可能性が高い
Almost everything I just said has been observed in the past.
私が今述べたことのほとんどすべてが過去に観察されています。
that climate change
その気候変動
Climate Change in the 21st Century
21世紀の気候変動
of course we have nothing
もちろん私たちには何もありません
no observational data
観測データがない
only by this mode
このモードだけで
that pattern
そのパターン
Predicting the 21st Century
21世紀を予測する
Global warming is 3 to 6 times that of the 20th century
地球温暖化は20世紀の3～6倍
3 to 6 times of 0.6 is almost 1.8
0.6の3～6倍はほぼ1.8
That is to say, 2 degrees to 4 degrees
つまり2度から4度
I told you when I started
始めた時にも言いましたが
There are about 2 degrees to 4 degrees
2度から4度くらいあります
What about greenhouse gases
温室効果ガスについてはどうですか
Sea level rise is basically 20 cm to 60 cm
海面上昇は基本的に20cm～60cm
The media often say 4 to 8 meters
メディアでは4～8メートルとよく言われます。
And then said that Taipei is gone
そして、台北はなくなったと言いました
Kaohsiung is gone
高雄はなくなった
I can type this question, I really want to ask
この質問を入力できます。本当に聞きたいのですが
hands up
手を挙げて
A few people saw the government's 2 degrees C
政府の気温2℃を見た人は数人いる
i'm quite a lot
私はかなり多いです
nearly half
ほぼ半分
The government's 2 degrees C should have a positive effect on adults
政府の気温2℃は成人にも良い影響を与えるはずだ
I've heard it's often
よくあると聞いた
Even primary schools have to go to see the government 2 degrees C
小学校でも気温2℃で政府に会いに行かなければなりません
middle school let alone
中学生どころか
The government's second-degree district almost sees it every day
政府の第二級選挙区はほぼ
Then I think it should be harmful to them
それなら、それは彼らにとって有害で​​あるべきだと思います
why come
なぜ来るのか
Because of the government's second-degree zone although it has many positive effects
政府の第 2 度ゾーンのおかげで、多くのプラスの効果があるものの、
He said when you miss his handprint
あなたが彼の手形を見逃したとき、彼は言いました
Dean Wuyue has all gone
ディーン・ウーユエは全員去ってしまった
i was invited
私は招かれました
But my position is far behind
でも私の立場ははるかに後ろです
very back
とても戻ってきました
that
それか
but
しかし
this
これ
Ms. Chen Wenqian actually ran up to shake hands
陳文謙さんは実際に握手を求めに駆け寄った
but that's no use
でもそれは無駄だ
I wrote one the next day
次の日も書きました
not the next day
次の日ではない
On the third day, I wrote an article saying
3日目にこんな記事を書きました。
why there
なぜそこに
most important
最も重要な
The information is actually wrong
実はその情報は間違っている
The most important information in it is
その中で最も重要な情報は、
With me
私と一緒に
I said hear this
これを聞いてと言いました
he spoke
彼は話した
That means the sea level will rise six meters
つまり海面は6メートル上昇することになる
Then it is said that it is likely to rise by 6 meters in 2035
その後、2035年には6メートル高くなる可能性があると言われています
I'll just say you hypothetically really believe in 2035
仮にあなたが 2035 年のことを本当に信じていると仮定して言っておきます
If the sea level were to rise six meters
海面が6メートル上昇した場合
you go home and see the one in your house
家に帰って家にあるものを見ると
How far is it from sea level now
今海面からどれくらい離れていますか
Average distance from sea level to Taipei
海面から台北までの平均距離
Only four meters above sea level
海抜わずか4メートル
The average means that half of the people are within four meters.
平均すると、半数の人が4メートル以内にいるということになります。
Let alone six meters
6メートルどころか
How much is left in 2035
2035年にはあとどれくらい残っているのか
How much is ten or twenty left?
10 または 20 はいくら残っていますか?
twenty four years
二十四年
Suppose my twenty-four years later
私の24年後を想像してみてください
if my house will be under the sea
もし私の家が海の中にあったら
Then I'll sell the house right now
それなら今すぐ家を売ります
Otherwise, when you see it, everyone will sell you
そうしないと、それを見たときにみんながあなたを売るでしょう
money is gone
お金がなくなった
I can not afford it
私はそうする余裕がない
so so but that's fine too
まあまあだけどそれもいいよ
That is to say, so many of us
つまり、私たちの多くは
everyone went to see
みんな見に行きました
People rarely think about selling their house.
家を売ろうと考える人はほとんどいません。
So it means that our education level in Taiwan
つまり、台湾の教育レベルは
It is indeed relatively high
確かに比較的高いですね
have your own judgment
自分の判断を持ってください
this is very important
これはとても重要です
Actually, I'm not just a joke
実は冗談じゃないんです
i traveled a lot
たくさん旅行しました
In fact, we are Taiwan
実は私たちは台湾なのです
This level of education
このレベルの教育
Everyone's attempt is relatively high
全員の挑戦は比較的高い
I tell you it is definitely taller than Americans
アメリカ人より間違いなく背が高いと言う
american until now
今までアメリカ人
You see, 40% of people believe
ほら、40%の人が信じてる
that what
それは何ですか
when our world began
私たちの世界が始まったとき
almost 4000 years ago
約4000年前
He still believes so
彼は今でもそう信じている
Let alone how he would believe
ましてや彼がどうやって信じるだろうか
this greenhouse gas
この温室効果ガス
these things
これらの事
This sea level is rising
この海面は上昇している
4 to 8 meters
4～8メートル
This is needed
これは必要です
At least like that whole pawn in Greenland
少なくともグリーンランドのあのポーン全体のように
Soldiers on land melt
陸上の兵士が溶ける
That pawn melted
そのポーンは溶けた
It is estimated that the total melting is 7 meters
総融解量は7メートルと推定されている
If it is said that the soldiers in Antarctica melted a part
南極の兵士が一部を溶かしたと言われれば
Then that will be 4 to 8 meters beyond this
そうすると、そこから4～8メートル先になります。
OK
OK
But this
しかしこれは
Soldiers in Greenland and the Melting of Soldiers in Antarctica
グリーンランドの兵士と南極の兵士の溶解
current melting rate
現在の融解速度
Some say fast, some say slow
速いという人もいるし、遅いという人もいる
This is currently very uncertain
これは現時点では非常に不確実です
Of course, this variable value is very large
もちろん、この変数値は非常に大きいです
The indeterminate value is large
不定値が大きい
Nor can it be exaggerated to say that it is unlimited
無制限と言っても過言ではありません
ah
ああ
There are many problems in this aspect of Zhenfu Erdu
この点に関して鎮府二都市には多くの問題がある
As for the dean of his fifteenth hospital, he is aware of the importance of this issue
15番目の病院の院長は、この問題の重要性を認識している
that i believe that is a very good
それはとても良いことだと私は信じています
result
結果
21st Century Climate Change
21世紀の気候変動
In addition, of course, the number of extremely high temperature days will increase.
また、当然、超高温日も増えていきます。
Decrease in the number of extremely low temperature days
極低温日の減少
drought will be worse
干ばつはさらに悪化するだろう
it's a sure thing
それは確かなことだ
In addition it has
さらに、それは
This is of course taken from the IPCC
もちろんこれはIPCCから引用したものです
That is to say
つまり
the one from the intergovernment group
政府間グループからのもの
climate panel results
気候パネルの結果
it was originally in 2007
もともとは2007年のことでした
The next one is to talk about in 2014
次回は2014年のお話です
to bring up
育てるため
In 2007 it also said
2007年にはこうも言った
Typhoons and torrential rains are likely to increase
台風や集中豪雨が増加する可能性があります
will be more serious
もっと深刻になるだろう
Now basically it's been
今は基本的にそうなっている
think this part
この部分を考えてください
typhoons will increase
台風が増えるだろう
or worse
あるいはさらに悪いことに
I don't think it's clear now
今は明らかではないと思います
But the rain will increase
でも雨は強くなるよ
wait for us
私たちを待ってください
Of course the question
もちろん質問は
discuss with you
あなたと話し合う
The increase in temperature just mentioned
先ほど述べた気温の上昇
it is mainly
それは主にです
To see how we reduce greenhouse gases
温室効果ガスをどのように削減するかを確認するには
how to decide
どうやって決めるか
will increase the minimum temperature by 1.8 degrees
最低気温が1.8度上昇します
is called B1
B1と呼ばれます
it is very optimistic
それはとても楽観的です
that is
あれは
current carbon dioxide
現在の二酸化炭素
Current global average emissions
現在の世界の平均排出量
is almost 4 metric tons
それは約4トンです
basically means
基本的に意味するのは
we start now
今から始めます
Keep at 4 metric tons per person
1人あたり4トンを維持してください
assuming that
仮定して
we can keep in
私たちはそこに留まることができます
The temperature increase will only reach 1.8 degrees
気温上昇は1.8度にとどまる
in this case
この場合
by 2100
2100年までに
CO2 will only increase to 450 PPM
CO2 は 450 PPM までしか増加しません
It's almost 400 now
もう400近くになってる
So this seems unlikely
したがって、これは可能性が低いように思われます
will definitely exceed
間違いなく超えるだろう
more than one case
複数のケース
called A2 case
A2ケースと呼ばれる
Name case
名入れ
basically follow nature
基本的に自然に従う
Don't worry about it
ご心配なく
continue to emit greenhouse gases
温室効果ガスを排出し続ける
in that case
その場合
In 210 it loves carbon dioxide
210年は二酸化炭素が大好き
would increase to almost 840 PPM
ほぼ 840 PPM まで増加します
That is three times the pre-industrial revolution
これは産業革命前の3倍です
in this case
この場合
Global warming is almost four degrees
地球温暖化はほぼ4度です
This is of course what I just mentioned
これはもちろん今お話ししたことです
The situation of B1 and A2 mentioned to you
あなたが話したB1とA2の状況
Let's draw the picture just now
さっそく絵を描いてみましょう
On the map of 1000 years ago
1000年前の地図で
What we just saw was 1000 years
私たちが今見たのは1000年
then 100 years
それから100年
Now add another 100 years
さらに 100 年追加します
is here
ここにある
Everyone noticed this rise
誰もがこの上昇に気づきました
it feels pretty scary
かなり怖い感じがします
from this angle
この角度から
This estimate of sea level rise
この海面上昇の推定値
also estimated
も推定されています
The current one, of course, is what we just saw
もちろん、現在のものは今見たものです
Using the results obtained in the last century
前世紀に得られた成果を活用して
This is the predicted result
これが予測結果です
This forecast is the IPCC's 2007 forecast
この予測は IPCC の 2007 年の予測です
Later at the meeting in Copenhagen
その後コペンハーゲンでの会合で
An impromptu estimate of sea level rise
海面上昇の即席推定
There are some people who think that the sea level will rise faster
海面上昇が早くなると考えている人もいる
make an estimate
見積もりをする
even faster people
さらに速い人
did you notice
気づきましたか
By the year 2000, they estimate, of course, there are uncertainties
2000 年までには、もちろん不確実性があると彼らは見積もっています
At most, it is slightly more than one meter to 2000 years
せいぜい1メートル強から2000年程度
His middle point is still less than a meter
彼の中間点はまだ1メートル未満です
Still less than a meter
まだ1メートルにも満たない
that
それか
rather than
それよりも
Both are 6 meters
どちらも6メートルです
6 meters as mentioned by IPCC
IPCCが言及した6メートル
is problematic
問題がある
Of course centuries later
もちろん何世紀も経ってから
Will it be 6 meters
6メートルになるでしょうか
i think about greenhouse gases
温室効果ガスについて考えます
if you continue
続ければ
centuries later
数世紀後
Of course it is possible to increase to 6 meters
もちろん6メートルまで伸ばすことも可能です
but we also know
しかし、私たちも知っています
in petroleum gas
石油ガスの中で
I'm afraid before 2050
2050年までには怖い
basically
基本的
No LOT of Petroleum Gas
石油ガスを大量に使用しない
ready to dig
掘る準備ができています
the coal itself
石炭そのもの
Of course there are almost 100 more years
もちろんあと100年近くある
can dig
掘ることができます
but by then
でもそれまでに
carbon dioxide emissions
二酸化炭素排出量
It is very uncertain
非常に不確実です
so this
したがって、この
that is to say centuries later
つまり数世紀後
This layout is very stable
このレイアウトは非常に安定しています
That use value is very small
その使用価値は非常に小さいです
I just talked about global issues
先ほど地球規模の問題について話しました
here back to us Taiwan
ここで私たちの台湾に戻ります
Our Taiwan has increased in the past almost 100 years
私たちの台湾は過去ほぼ100年間で増加しました
The temperature increase is applied on the
温度上昇は、
that past 100 years
過去100年
That 100+ year global temperature increase is undercoated
100年以上にわたる地球の気温上昇は下塗りされている
you can see
見ることができます
it looks like that
そのように見えます
First a temperature increase
まずは気温上昇
then relatively flat
その後は比較的平坦
Then another temperature increase
その後また気温が上昇
this looks like
これは次のようです
This also means that we Taiwan is part of the global warming
これは、台湾に住む私たちも地球温暖化に加担していることを意味します
But our warming
しかし、私たちの温暖化は
Let’s talk about it carefully to see how much it heats up
どれくらい熱くなるか、じっくり話しましょう
is global warming
地球温暖化です
Let's say the 20th century was almost twice the global warming
20 世紀はほぼ 2 倍の地球温暖化があったとしましょう
The reason is now quite clear to us
その理由は今では非常に明らかです
Mainly due to the influence of urban heat conduction effect
主に都市熱伝導効果の影響による
Influence of Urban Thermal Conductivity Effect
都市の熱伝導率効果の影響
also takes us from 1961 to the present
1961 年から現在まで
almost 50 years
ほぼ50年
our main warming
私たちの主な温暖化
Taiwan mainly heats up at night
台湾は主に夜に暑くなります
rarely heats up during the day
日中暑くなることはほとんどありません
it's very interesting
とても興味深いです
OK
OK
wait we can see
待ってください、見えます
in addition
加えて
is that our rainfall intensity is changing
降雨量が変化しているということです
this is my personal opinion
これは私の個人的な意見です
Let's assume we're really worried about things in Taiwan
私たちが台湾のことを本当に心配していると仮定しましょう
It's a matter of rainfall intensity
それは雨の強さの問題です
The intensity of the rainfall and the heat wave
雨の強さと熱波
are all changes that can be called extreme weather
異常気象ともいえる変化はすべて
we know extreme weather is random
私たちは異常気象がランダムであることを知っています
This global warming changes
この地球温暖化は変化をもたらします
The most obvious one is of course a heat wave.
最もわかりやすいのは、もちろん熱波です。
The change of that heavy rain and light rain
あの大雨と小雨の移り変わり
Also extreme weather changes
異常気象の変化も
What about this change?
この変更についてはどうですか?
From the point of view of this pattern
このパターンから見ると
is very very difficult to predict
予測するのは非常に非常に困難です
that almost all patterns
それはほぼ全てのパターン
There will be problems in this area
この分野では問題が起きるだろう
so what
だから何
This IPCC
このIPCC
The impact of this extreme weather
この異常気象の影響
Although there are
ありますが、
have done this for sure
これは確かにやった
It will become more and more powerful
どんどんパワーアップしていきますね
But he is still quite conservative
しかし彼は依然としてかなり保守的だ
wait a minute we can see
ちょっと待ってください、見えます
why is it like this
なぜこんなことになっているのか
Ah Taiwan heat wave
ああ台湾の猛暑
This is us
これが私たちです
One made in 2009
2009年に作られたもの
That Causa is our Posta Xu Qianzhong
その原因は私たちのPosta Xu Qianzhongです
Then there is Chen Zhengping, a professor at National Taiwan University.
次に、国立台湾大学の陳正平教授です。
That
それか
here it is
ここにあります
Taiwan
台湾
But from 1961 to 2005
ただし、1961 年から 2005 年まで
45-year mean temperature change
45年間の平均気温変化
it's daytime
昼間です
bottom is night
下は夜です
blue is to reduce the temperature
青は温度を下げる
red is to increase the temperature
赤は温度を上げることです
Everyone knows it at a glance
誰でも一目でわかる
increase temperature at night
夜の気温を上げる
especially ayutthaya
特にアユタヤ
increased temperature during the day
日中の気温の上昇
real decent increase
本当にまともな増加
only this station
この駅だけ
Only the station is 3.5 kilometers away from the budget
予算からは駅まで3.5キロしか離れていない
Of course he does not represent Taiwan
もちろん彼は台湾代表ではない
he actually represents
彼は実際に代表しています
Represents the change in temperature over a large area
広い範囲の温度変化を表します
So if you take Yushan away
それで玉山を奪ったら
Average daytime temperature in Taiwan
台湾の日中の平均気温
actually cooling down
実際に冷める
What is the real reason for the cooling
冷える本当の理由とは
We also have quite a large thinning now
かなり大規模な間伐も行われています
It's the polluted gas that we exhale
それは私たちが吐き出す汚染ガスです
polluted gas
汚染ガス
reflect sunlight back during the day
日中に太陽光を反射する
so we environmental rats
だから私たち環境ネズミは
working harder now
今はもっと頑張って
They really worked hard
彼らは本当に一生懸命働きました
Taiwan's pollution is getting less and less
台湾の汚染はますます減少しています
look carefully
よく見て
especially taipei
特に台北
In the past 15 or 20 years in Taipei
ここ15年か20年台北で
Especially the reduction of this preemptive pollution
特にこの先制的な汚染の削減
more than doubled
2倍以上になった
so this is pretty good
これはかなり良いです
But it also means
しかし、それはまた意味します
In the future we will be more and more
これからも私たちはもっともっと
The EPA is getting harder
EPAはますます難しくなる
What we pay will go back to the card
支払った金額はカードに返金されます
OK
OK
At night because the sun has no effect
夜は太陽の影響がないので
night temperature global warming
夜の気温 地球温暖化
heated
加熱された
Then there is the thermal conduction effect also heating up
熱伝導効果もあって加熱します
So it gets hotter at night
だから夜は暑くなるんです
look at taipei
台北を見てください
Between 45 years
45歳以上の間
45 years of global increase
45年間にわたる世界的な増加
A staggering 0.5 degrees increase
驚異の0.5度上昇
Here it increases almost 2 degrees
ここでは2度近く気温が上がります
2 degrees increase at night
夜は2度上昇
The result in Taipei was quite a bad result
台北の結果はかなり散々な結果だった
As you can see, Taiwan is Taiwan without Taipei.
ご覧のとおり、台湾は台北なしの台湾です。
This is a different place in Taiwan as a whole
ここは台湾のどこでも違う場所です
Different colors represent different places
異なる色は異なる場所を表します
Minimum temperature over 25 at night
夜の最低気温が25度以上
number of days in a year
一年の日数
OK
OK
Blue represents Taipei
青は台北を表します
did you notice
気づきましたか
look
見て
It's over 25 degrees tonight
今夜は25度超えです
Said it was over 25 degrees outside
外気温は25度以上だったそうです
It must be definitely over 26 degrees in there
間違いなく26度以上あるはず
The government even allows you to turn on the air conditioner
政府はエアコンをつけることさえ許可している
So at that time, everyone must turn on the air-conditioning
だからその時はみんなエアコンをつけなきゃいけない
This air-conditioned night from before 1960
1960年以前のエアコンの効いたこの夜
There are only more than 30 days when the air conditioner needs to be turned on at night
夜間にエアコンをオンにする必要がある日は 30 日程度です。
Now you see more than 100 days
100 日以上が表示されます
Taipei needs to turn on the air conditioner at night
台北は夜はエアコンをオンにする必要があります
tripled
3倍になった
This actually affects
これは実際に影響を及ぼします
very huge
非常大的
Just say no wonder our Aiyanghua carbon brand
当社の Aiyanghua カーボン ブランドも不思議ではありません。
Everyone's brand is better than the whole world
みんなのブランドは全世界よりも優れている
How much more are we than the world average
私たちは世界平均よりどれくらい高いのか
Does anyone know
誰か知っていますか
three times
三倍
someone knows this
誰かがこれを知っています
This is also one of the reasons
これも理由の一つです
look
見て
Taiwan in summer
夏の台湾
The air conditioner is basically turned on everywhere at night
夜間は基本的にどこでもエアコンがオンになります
that all
それすべて
The other two big cities are not much better
他の 2 つの大都市はそれほど良くありません
Black
黒
the second most increased
2番目に増えた
The same goes for Tainan and Taichung
台南や台中も同様です
Almost all Taiwan
ほぼどこでも
The phenomenon of drinking more and drinking less
飲酒量が増えたり減ったりする現象
Although urban
都会的でありながらも
I just said that it is urban heat conduction effect
先ほど都市熱伝導効果と言いましたが、
But for us in Taiwan as a whole
しかし、台湾全体としては
because of the population density
人口密度のせいで
We have all guides
私たちはすべてのガイドを持っています
The tendency of the kind of thermal conduction effect
熱伝導効果の種類の傾向
time relationship
時間の関係
I won't show you this picture
この写真は見せません
Tell me about the heat island effect
ヒートアイランド現象について教えてください
This is Chuo University Shake Center
こちらは中央大学シェイクセンターです
Provided by Professor Liu
劉教授提供
This is Taichung area
ここは台中エリアです
you see build plants
植物を建てるのがわかります
Paddy field next to Dadu West
大肚西の隣の水田
You see purple against this dark green
この濃い緑に紫が見えるね
dark green here purple
濃い緑、ここは紫
about six degrees
約6度
This is a very cold effect
これは非常に寒い効果です
daytime
昼間
daytime heat wave
昼間の熱波
OK
OK
At one point we said that the EPA said it was going to put a heat wave rack
ある時点で私たちは、EPAが熱波ラックを設置するつもりだと述べたと言いました。
or when the heat wave comes
あるいは熱波が来ると
outdoor sports
アウトドアスポーツ
Manual workers get a raise
肉体労働者は昇給する
I will show him this about our Taiwan
私は彼に私たちの台湾についてこれを見せます
Days when the temperature exceeds 36 degrees
気温が36度を超える日
Also different colors and different places
色も違うし場所も違う
The real high temperature exceeds 36 degrees
本当の最高気温は36度を超える
looks a bit increased
少し増えたように見える
The obvious increase is my blue desk
明らかに増えたのは私の青い机です
Taipei is Taipei
台北は台北だよ
Then, just look at the words of Taipei
それでは、台北の言葉を見てください。
Of course it's not about global warming.
もちろん地球温暖化の問題ではありません。
It is all related to the thermal conductivity effect
それはすべて熱伝導率の効果に関係しています
and the increase is not so large
そして増加幅はそれほど大きくない
Because this is 36 degrees
36度なので
If you say it is 38 degrees
38度って言ったら
I believe this is not just a one or two day relationship
これは1日や2日だけの関係ではないと思います
So heat waves are basically not too serious a problem
したがって、熱波は基本的にそれほど深刻な問題ではありません
in Taiwan
台湾で
And the really serious problem is that we
そして本当に深刻な問題は、
The results of a study done in 2009
2009年に行われた研究結果
as far back as almost 10 years ago
遡ること10年近く前まで
we noticed this
私たちはこれに気づきました
in Taiwan
台湾で
all of taiwan
台湾全土
Here is an article from our 2002
こちらは2002年の記事です
He just said that his information will be pushed back
彼は自分の情報は差し戻されるだろうと言いました
This is all the rainfall in Taiwan
台湾の雨はこれだけです
Average rainfall throughout the year
年間平均降水量
This line is an average of 2 3 1 5mm
この線は 2 3 1 5mm の平均です
up and down
上下
But there is no long-term change
しかし長期的には変化がない
The second graph is the number of hours we have rain
2 番目のグラフは雨が降った時間数です。
it goes up and down
それは上がったり下がったりします
But it has a long-term change
しかし長期的な変化はある
Total rainfall is derived from rainfall hours
総降雨量は降雨時間から導き出されます
that's the intensity of the rain
それは雨の強さです
did you notice
気づきましたか
When the rainfall intensity reached almost 80 years
降雨量が80年近くに達したとき
all of a sudden increase
突然増えた
increase
増加
just increased
増えただけ
to a similar extent
同様の程度に
The average is almost 3 2.9
平均はほぼ 3 2.9
Then this has increased by almost 1
すると、これはほぼ1倍になりました
That is an increase of 30%
それは 30% の増加です
rainfall intensity
降雨強度
increased by 30%
30%増加
That's another point of view
それは別の視点です
I just explained this to you
私はこれをあなたに説明したばかりです
say every 10 years on average
平均すると10年ごとに
heavy rain here
ここで大雨が降る
It's raining here
ここは雨が降っています
it has this tendency
この傾向があります
Increase in heavy rainfall
大雨の増加
Moderate rain decreases
中程度の雨が減少
The whole world has seen this
全世界がこれを見た
We analyze the data of the United States
米国のデータを分析します
Also heavy rainfall is increasing
大雨も増えています
Moderate rain hasn't changed much
適度な雨はあまり変わらない
This America is a comparison
このアメリカは比較対象です
interesting example
興味深い例
is total rainfall in the United States is increasing
米国の総降雨量は増加しています
This is different from Taiwan
台湾とはここが違う
Our total rainfall in Taiwan
台湾の総降雨量
very little change
ほとんど変化がありません
But America North America
でもアメリカ北米
Total rainfall is increasing
総降水量は増加している
The result of this is
この結果は次のとおりです
Its heavy rainfall increases even more
その大雨はさらに増加し​​ます
not just
だけでなく
I mean the whole world has seen it
つまり全世界がそれを見たということです
Increase in heavy rainfall
大雨の増加
Moderate rain decreases
中程度の雨が減少
this in theory
これは理論的には
now more and more mature
今ではますます成熟しています
Year 2003
2003年
spring bass
春贝斯他
they published an article
彼らは記事を公開しました
put the past almost ten years
過去10年近くを考えると
A comparative summary of theoretical articles in this area
この分野の理論論文の比較概要
conclude
結論
It is basically now that the theory is getting more and more mature
基本的に理論はますます成熟しつつあります
It's just that its quantification is still not very certain
ただ、その定量化はまだあまり確実ではありません
it basically says
それは基本的に言う
According to the most basic principles of physics
物理学の最も基本的な原理によると
Just increase the temperature by one degree
温度を1度上げるだけ
Because most of the earth's surface is water
地球の表面のほとんどは水なので、
water vapor on the sea
海の水蒸気
temperature increased by one degree
気温が1度上昇
will increase by about seven Percent
約7パーセント増加します
said
言った
You added 7% more water vapor
水蒸気が 7% 増加しました
if nothing else remains the same
他に何も変わらないなら
Each rainfall should increase by 7%
降水量はそれぞれ 7% ずつ増加するはずです
But heavy rainfall will increase even more
しかし、大雨はさらに増えるでしょう
why
なぜ
Because 7% entered heavy rainfall
7%が豪雨に入ったため
Because heavy rainfall is usually a very large convective system
豪雨は通常、非常に大規模な対流システムであるため、
The convection system sucks in from the bottom
対流方式で底から吸い込みます
lots of air down there
そこにはたくさんの空気がある
its watery air
その水っぽい空気
So this water vapor has increased by 7%
つまり、この水蒸気は 7% 増加したことになります。
Once it enters the convection
対流に入ると
when it goes up
上がったとき
It was water vapor when it went up
上がってくると水蒸気だった
will become
となります
go up and get cold
上がって寒くなる
Turns into liquid water when cooled
冷却すると液体の水になります
From water vapor to liquid water
水蒸気から液体の水へ
it gives off what's called latent heat
いわゆる潜熱を放出します
Liquid water turns to ice
液体の水が氷に変わる
continue to emit shallow heat
浅い熱を放出し続ける
Emitting shallow heat is for the study of meteorology
浅い熱を発するのは気象学の研究のため
They think that making the convection more intense
彼らは対流をより激しくすると考えている
In other words, you originally only increased by 7%
言い換えれば、元々は 7% しか増加しなかったということです
But your convection is stronger
でも君の対流はもっと強いよ
That is to say, heavy rainfall
つまり大雨
The increase will be much more than 7%
増加率は7%を大きく超えるだろう
For this I used schematic
このために私は回路図を使用しました
That is to say, water vapor enters
つまり水蒸気が入ってくるのです
It emits a shallow heat after entering
入ってから浅い熱を発します
Then make the convective system more intense
次に、対流システムをより激しくします
This is our estimate
これは私たちの見積もりです
right to estimate
推定する権利
No, we were meant to do global
いいえ、私たちはグローバルに行うつもりでした
This is what we did for Taiwan
これが私たちが台湾のためにやったことです
Estimated using data from Taiwan
台湾のデータを使用して推定
What is this estimate?
この見積もりは何ですか?
That is, when the global temperature increases by one degree
つまり、地球の気温が1度上昇すると、
How will Taiwan's rainfall intensity change?
台湾の降雨量はどう変化するのでしょうか？
then i just said
それから私はちょうど言いました
Let's just divide Taiwan's annual rainfall into
台湾の年間降雨量を次のように分けてみましょう。
According to its rainfall intensity, it is divided into ten equal parts
降雨量の強さに応じて、10等分に分けられます。
Then we calculate the result that
次に、結果を計算します。
The strongest ten percent of heavy rainfall
最も強い10パーセントの豪雨
Just one degree increase in global temperature
地球の気温がたった1度上昇するだけ
It increased by almost 140%
ほぼ140%増加しました
almost doubled and a half
ほぼ2倍半
Just one degree increase in global temperature increases
たった1度上がるだけで地球の気温は上昇する
only heavy rainfall
大雨だけが降る
Thousands of ten percent heavy rainfall doubles and a half
10パーセントの豪雨が2.5倍に増加
The light rain is decreasing
小雨は小降りになってきました
are decreasing
減少しています
the impact of this
この影響
of course that means
もちろんそれは意味します
I think everyone can imagine
誰もが想像できると思います
that
それか
I was introducing this just now
先ほど紹介したところです
Just say the old one
昔のことだけ言ってよ
It was mentioned in ancient civilizations
古代文明で言及されていた
This heavy rainfall increases
この大雨はさらに増加し​​ます
This will increase flooding
そうなると洪水が増えるよ
ok
Ok
Then the top 10% is supposed to increase so much
そうすれば上位10%はかなり増えるはずです
then you can imagine
それから想像してみてください
We actually count the top 1%
実際には上位 1% をカウントします
Top 1% increase over 220%
上位 1% が 220% を超えて増加
we know this
私たちはこれを知っています
We counted the top 1%
上位 1% を数えました
the more intense kind of rain
より激しい種類の雨
10% stronger than 1% ahead
1% 先よりも 10% 強い
Almost all the heavy rainfall brought by the typhoon
台風による大雨のほとんどが
The top 1% more than tripled
上位1%は3倍以上
so this
したがって、この
global temperature increase
地球規模の気温上昇
Increased chance of landslides and floods
地滑りや洪水の可能性が高まる
will be very large
就会非常大
more than double more than double
2倍以上 2倍以上
the reduction of the light rain
小雨の減少
For example, in this
たとえば、これでは
winter and spring
冬と春
The rain in Taiwan is almost all light rain
台湾の雨はほとんど小雨です
After you reduce the light rain
小雨が弱まった後は
There will be problems with spring plowing in the second spring
2年目の春には春の耕起に問題が生じるだろう
If you take a closer look at Taiwan's spring situation
台湾の春事情を詳しく見てみると
Spring plowing to do a simple statistics
簡単な統計を行うための春の耕作
It can be noticed that the plowing rate of spring plowing in recent years
近年の春耕の耕起率が顕著であることがわかる。
Much higher than 50 years ago
50年前よりはるかに高い
Here I will give you a rough estimate.
ここで大まかなお見積りをさせていただきます。
1950 to 2005
1950年から2005年まで
global temperature increase
地球規模の気温上昇
almost very close to 0.7 degrees
ほぼ0.7度に近い
0.7% of each degree of Taiwan 140%
台湾の各学位の0.7% 140%
almost 100%
ほぼ100%
That is to say
つまり
You said it was this heavy rain that gave you
この大雨があなたに与えたのだとあなたは言いました
brought the words of the flood
洪水の言葉をもたらした
basically the basis of this flood
基本的にこの洪水の基礎
double the odds
確率が2倍になる
OK
OK
The light rain has also decreased relatively.
小雨も比較的減りました。
Then follow this effect
次に、この効果に従います
certainly
そうです
this is what we have seen
これが私たちが見たものです
what has happened
何が起きたの
Taiwan has
台湾には
that in addition
それに加えて
The IPCC
IPCC
It is estimated that by 2035
2035年までに
will increase by about 0.7 degrees
約0.7度上昇します
that is to say
つまり
what we just said
私たちが今言ったこと
turn it over again
もう一度ひっくり返す
OK
OK
So to this 2035
それでこの2035年まで
Taiwan's flood control
台湾の治水
Anti-landslide
防土石流
anti-sweat measures
汗対策
should be
あるべきです
in the 1950's
1950年代に
or earlier
それ以前の
These engineering facilities
これらのエンジニアリング施設は、
should be tripled
3倍にする必要があります
increase by 3 times
3倍に増加
sounds like it says yes
そうと言っているように聞こえる
we're going to take this
私たちはこれを取るつもりです
Project tripled
プロジェクトが3倍に
I did ask people
人に聞いてみたんですが
People say Tamsui River
人々は淡水川と言います
The entire Tamsui River Basin in Greater Taipei
台北都市部の淡水河流域全体
Increase this flood control project
この治水事業を増やしてください
don't say three times
トリプルとは言わないでください
even if you double
倍にしても
do it again
再びそれを行う
He said do it again
彼はもう一度やりましょうと言った
how much do you want
いくら欲しいですか
He said to use photos to count
彼は写真を使って数えると言った
that is
あれは
so this
したがって、この
Questions like this
このような質問
ah british
ああ、イギリス人
Because special attention has been paid to this aspect of climate change
気候変動のこの側面に特別な注意が払われているため
they often come to my office
彼らはよく私のオフィスに来ます
to talk about this
これについて話すために
He said ah he said this is in our UK
彼は、ああ、ここは私たちのイギリスだと言いました
There is also this phenomenon
こんな現象もあります
I said we I told others
私は他の人にも言ったと言いました
This is what we need for flood control
治水に必要なのはこれだ
to find a way
方法を見つけるために
make him
彼にさせる
This flood protection measure re-enlarges it
この洪水防御策はそれを再拡大します
He said
彼は言った
I'm in the UK
私はイギリスにいます
we also say
私たちも言います
What a lot of engineering needs to be added
どれほど多くのエンジニアリングを追加する必要があるか
But the government never
しかし政府は決して
he said why not
彼はなぜそうしないのかと言いました
He said it makes sense
彼はそれは理にかなっていると言いました
Think about it
考えてみてください
he does this project
彼はこのプロジェクトをやっています
wait till it's done
終わるまで待ってください
timing
タイミング
Don't talk about four-year term
4年の任期については話さないでください
He served eight years
彼は8年間服役した
He can't even see when it's done
彼にはそれがいつ終わるのかさえ見えない
He said there wasn't even a single vote
一票も入ってなかったって言ってた
He said why to do it
彼はなぜそうするのかと言った
so they don't do it
だから彼らはそれをしない
so he suggested we
それで彼は私たちに提案しました
later in Taiwan
その後台湾で
set up a
成立一個
a complete
一個完全
independent
独立
completely independent
完全に独立した
How to say
どのように言って
to global warming
地球温暖化への
Oversight Team
監視チーム
like
好き
Great Britain was formed
イギリスが成立した
i miss us taiwan
台湾が恋しい
will not be established
確立されないだろう
basic solution
基本的な解決策
that
それか
of course we know
もちろん私たちは知っています
The basic solution is to prevent
根本的な解決策は予防することです
the mitigation
緩和策
Of course, stopping global warming can reduce carbon
もちろん、地球温暖化を阻止すれば炭素は削減できます
easier said than done
言うは易く行うは難し
show everyone
みんなに見せて
current carbon dioxide emissions
現在の二酸化炭素排出量
Still keep going up, all over the world
まだまだ上がり続けて 世界中で
Taiwan is not left behind
台湾も取り残されていない
I think I showed you this last time
前回もお見せしたと思いますが、
After 1980 to 2005
1980年以降～2005年
The grayest is our Taiwan
最も灰色なのは私たちの台湾です
Take a break from the American people to increase
アメリカ人から離れて増加する
More than 12 metric tons increased by 3 times
12トン以上が3倍に増加
The three worst countries in the world
世界で最悪の３カ国
we are now second only to them
私たちは今では彼らに次ぐ地位にあります
USA Australia and Canada
アメリカ、オーストラリア、カナダ
Of course there are some very small countries in the middle
もちろん、真ん中には非常に小さな国がいくつかあります
here is only count
ここにはカウントしかありません
A country with a population of more than 10 million
人口1,000万人を超える国
we are number four
私たちは4番目です
All Western European countries and Japan are under us
すべての西ヨーロッパ諸国と日本は私たちの下にあります
not to mention france
フランスは言うまでもありません
France is this one
フランスはこれだ
OK
OK
china is here
中国はここにあります
China is now more than five
中国は現在5カ国以上
It's over five now
もう5時過ぎだよ
What are the main differences between France and Taiwan?
フランスと台湾の主な違いは何ですか?
Does anyone know
誰か知っていますか
nuclear power
原子力
Nuclear Power Now Sounds Dirty World
原子力発電は今、汚い世界のように聞こえます
but
しかし
This is mainly
これは主に
France is different from us
フランスは私たちとは違う
Of course we're going to take us from 12 metric tons
もちろん、12トンから取るつもりです
reduced to 4 metric tons
4トンに削減
Because the target is 4 metric tons
目標は4トンなので
we are now
私たちは今
Actually we may be over 12 metric tons
実際には12トンを超える可能性があります
to reduce to 4 metric tons
4トンまで削減する
our estimate
私たちの見積もり
Saving and improving efficiency may be almost 65% from 12-4
節約と効率の向上は 12-4 からほぼ 65% になる可能性があります
20% of them may be saved and improved efficiency can be achieved
そのうちの 20% が節約され、効率が向上する可能性があります。
Here I specifically mentioned putting in a vegetarian
ここで私は特にベジタリアンを取り入れることについて言及しました
Vegetarianism is actually a very effective way
菜食主義は実際には非常に効果的な方法です
But it's easier said than done
しかし、言うは易く行うは難し
I'm basically a vegetarian for two days a week
私は基本的に週に2日はベジタリアンです
I'm not bad at other times
他の時は悪くないよ
Vegetarianism is not only that it can save a lot of greenhouse gases
菜食主義は温室効果ガスを大量に節約できるだけではありません
It's on top of the greenhouse gases we're putting in right now
それは私たちが現在導入している温室効果ガスの上にあります
it is slow to come out
出てくるのが遅いです
It will basically take 100 years to come out
出てくるまでに基本的に100年かかる
100 years after we put it in now, it will still be heated for at least 50 years
今入れてから100年後、少なくとも50年は加熱されます。
Still at home a hundred years later
百年経ってもまだ家にいる
Most of it will come out in a hundred years
そのほとんどは100年以内に明らかになるだろう
But if you say vegetarian
でもベジタリアンって言ったら
very powerful
とてもパワフルな
vegetarian words
ベジタリアンの言葉
If you say that many people are vegetarian
ベジタリアンの人が多いと言ったら
That's a lot of them now dedicated to raising cattle and sheep.
現在、その多くが牛や羊の飼育に専念している。
Like Brazil he burned many souls
ブラジルのように、彼は多くの命を燃やした
It's all about raising cattle and sheep
すべては牛と羊を育てることです
then sell
それから売る
European places such as the United States and the United Kingdom
アメリカやイギリスなどのヨーロッパの地域
A lot of farmland it can return to life
活気を取り戻せる農地がたくさんある
Because vegetarians need very little food
ベジタリアンは食べ物をほとんど必要としないので、
a lot less
はるかに少ないです
If there is not so much food
食べ物があまりない場合
A lot of land can be released
多くの土地を解放できる
back to life
生き返る
It sucks carbon dioxide directly from the air
空気中から二酸化炭素を直接吸引します
down
下
food very fast
食べ物はとても早い
several years
数年
can be done in a few years
数年以内にはできるだろう
If you don't believe me, it's true that none of us are vegetarians.
私の言うことが信じられないかもしれませんが、私たちの中にベジタリアンがいないのは本当です。
and say vegetarian
そしてベジタリアンと言う
In fact, I am also quite excited
実際、私もかなり興奮しています。
Because every time I say vegetarian
だって私がベジタリアンって言うたびに
People always say oops best man ever
人々はいつも「おっと史上最高の男」と言います
I also think it's hard to eat meat, but it tastes better
肉も食べにくいと思うけど美味しいです
But what?
でも何？
But do you know that when I was in college
でも、私が大学にいたときのことを知っていますか？
i have already said
私はすでに言いました
everyone is younger than me
みんな私より年下です
I didn't expect to go to college
大学に行くとは思わなかった
I am Taichung No.1 Middle School
私は台中第一中学校です。
Treasure to send big
大きく送る宝物
OK
OK
Chengda has only three restaurants
成大にはレストランが3軒しかない
There are only three restaurants for boys
男子向けのレストランは3軒しかない
a girl restaurant
女の子のレストラン
our boys restaurant
私たちのボーイズレストラン
Everyone loves that third restaurant
誰もがその 3 番目のレストランが大好きです
It is better than modern
現代よりも優れている
Things to eat
食べ物
we run every time
私たちは毎回走ります
run to everyone
みんなのところへ走る
we were
私たちはいた
I'm basically never full
基本的に満腹になることはありません
I'm never full for breakfast
朝食でお腹がいっぱいになることはありません
That
それか
at that time
その時
I was in Chengda for four years
私は成達に4年間いました
that
それか
that rice bag
あの米袋
The price of the package meal has never changed
パッケージミールの価格は変わりません
That
それか
guess how much a month
月にいくらだと思いますか
how much?
いくら？
any left?
少し残っている？
Some people say 90
90という人もいる
Wow
おお
If 90
90の場合
I tell you
私はあなたに言います
I'm not here today
今日はここにいません
Then
それから
that
それか
I was
私はそうでした
this is really
ほんとに
It's the wind that blows
吹くのは風だ
i feel a little bit
少し感じます
thin feeling
薄い感じ
at that time i
その時私は
Often less than 60 kg
60kg未満の場合が多い
I now
今私は
75 kg
75kg
How much difference do you see
どのくらい違いがわかりますか
I'm not so fat now
今はそんなに太ってないよ
It was good at that time
あの時は良かった
we had breakfast
私たちは朝食を食べました
90 is really
90は本当に
a month
月
Think about it 180 a month
月に180回考えてください
one day
ある日
How many
多少
6 pieces
6個
A meal is only 2 yuan
食事はたったの2元
At that time, breakfast was less than two yuan
当時、朝食は2元未満でした。
I guess for breakfast I'm afraid he put a dollar in it
朝食用に、彼は1ドルを入れたのではないかと思います
The porridge we ate for breakfast
朝食に食べたお粥
pick that up
それを拾う
You can't eat two bowls
二杯は食べられないよ
ok then you say run faster
わかった、じゃあもっと早く走れって言うね
In the morning, I ran to fish the bottom
朝、底を釣りに走った
This water will know me too
この水も私を知るだろう
but that cook is smarter than you
でもその料理人はあなたより賢いです
they are not less
彼らもそれ以下ではない
He cooked the porridge
彼はお粥を調理しました
Let’s just say the rice grains and the water
米粒と水で言えば
no matter what height you put
どの高さに置いても
it weighs the same
その重さは同じです
It's the same wherever you dig
どこを掘っても同じだ
just like rivers and lakes
川や湖と同じように
So you eat, some people say why don’t you eat steamed buns
だから食べる、肉まんを食べたらどうだという人もいる
I want to say when I hear this
これを聞いたら言いたい
I said oops there's a king in France
ああ、フランスには王がいる、と私は言った
The lady said the sign up was hungry
女性はサインアップはお腹が空いていると言った
no bread
パンがありません
He said how could these idiots not eat
彼はこう言った、どうしてこの愚か者たちが食べられないのか
do you want cake
ケーキは食べますか？
That no no no no steamed buns
いやいやいや蒸しパン
it's like saying
と言っているようなものです
It's not good for you to eat porridge
お粥を食べるのは良くない
Are you going to eat steamed buns?
蒸しパンを食べますか？
If there were steamed buns, I would not weigh 60 kg
まんじゅうがあったら体重は60kgにならないよ
I mean
つまり
I used to eat very little meat
昔は肉をほとんど食べなかった
It's actually healthy
実は健康的なんです
Just give us some steamed buns in the morning
朝は肉まんをください
That should actually be passable
それは実際には許容範囲であるはずです
That also means
それはまた、
That means we eat meat in Taiwan now
ということは、台湾では今も肉を食べているということですね
When do you think we eat meat
私たちがいつ肉を食べると思いますか
Actually very recently
実はつい最近まで
I'm afraid it will be 20 or 30 years.
20年か30年かかると思います。
even americans
アメリカ人でさえ
The American who first started eating meat
初めて肉を食べ始めたアメリカ人
Guess when
いつだろう
after World War II
第二次世界大戦後
They just started eating meat
彼らは肉を食べ始めたばかりです
before World War II
第二次世界大戦前
they didn't eat the meat
彼らは肉を食べませんでした
the best proof is
最良の証拠は
1928 call for presidential campaign pioneer
1928年大統領選挙運動の先駆者を募集
He said you choose my words
彼はあなたが私の言葉を選ぶと言った
he said i promise
彼は約束すると言いました
a chicken in every part
あらゆる部位にチキンが入っている
ah yes
ああ、そうだね
Chicken is the cheapest meat in America
鶏肉はアメリカで最も安い肉です
chicken
鶏
He said you just choose me
彼はあなたが私を選ぶだけだと言いました
i promise you go home
家に帰ると約束する
Every night there is a chicken in that pot
毎晩その鍋には鶏肉が入っています
he chose
彼が選びました
So what does this represent?
では、これは何を意味するのでしょうか？
Let's say in 1928 most people in the United States
1928年に米国のほとんどの人が
no chicken for dinner
夕食に鶏肉はありません
because if there is chicken to eat
なぜなら、食べる鶏肉があれば
why choose it
なぜそれを選ぶのか
so that
となることによって
Then I didn't have to eat for 28 years
それから28年間何も食べる必要がなかった
as you can imagine
あなたが想像できるように
later in the 1930s
1930年代後半
Needless to say
言うまでもなく
America in the 1930s
1930年代のアメリカ
the Great Panic
大パニック
it's over
終わりました
then fight
それから戦う
Not to mention what kind of meat to eat when fighting a war
戦争中にどのような肉を食べるかは言うまでもありません
so basically
だから基本的に
The United States probably didn't eat meat until the 1950s
米国はおそらく1950年代まで肉を食べていなかった
Europe is nothing compared to the 60s
ヨーロッパは60年代に比べれば何でもない
Nothing like the 70s, our 80s
70年代や80年代のようなものはありません
Mainland China in the 1990s OK
1990 年代の中国本土
so we eat meat is very recent
だから私たちが肉を食べるのはごく最近のことです
We were generally not meat-eating animals in the past
私たちは昔は一般的に肉を食べる動物ではありませんでした
Eating so much meat is actually bad for your health
肉を食べすぎると実は健康に悪い
So here's a chance to spread the word
だから、この言葉を広めるチャンスです
Naf carbon energy
ナフカーボンエネルギー
Of course this is not possible
もちろんそんなことは不可能です
I guess vegetarians can't do it
ベジタリアンには無理だと思う
So always look for non-carbon energy
したがって、常に非炭素エネルギーを探してください
Take a look at non-carbon energy
非炭素エネルギーを見てみましょう
Solar energy is of course endless
太陽エネルギーはもちろん無限です
but expensive
しかし高価な
If we all use solar energy
みんなで太陽エネルギーを使えば
Basically everyone does nothing
基本的にみんな何もしない
just buy solar
太陽光発電だけを買う
So water power wind power sea
だから水力 風力 海
This sounds good
これはいいですね
Right now, let's actually do it
さあ、実際にやってみましょう
we want to add
追加したい
Taiwan's water power is good
台湾の水力は素晴らしい
But it's all used up now
でももう全部使い終わってしまった
but about 2% to 3%
でも2%から3%くらい
that's pretty good too
それもかなりいいですね
Reproductive power can indeed be a lot
生殖力は確かに大きいかもしれない
But this reproductive energy is the same as food
しかし、この生殖エネルギーは食べ物と同じです
it you use a lot of food to grow
成長するにはたくさんの食べ物を使います
reproductive energy words
生殖エネルギーの言葉
This whole food is going to get really expensive
この食べ物全体は本当に高価になるだろう
So it's not very feasible
だからそれはあまり現実的ではない
what's left
何が残っているのか
After the earthquake in Japan, no one dared to say how
日本の地震の後、誰もそれがどのように起こったかを敢えて言わなかった
so i don't say anything
だから私は何も言いません
That is to say, there is no solution
つまり解決策はない
OK, this is actually unsolvable at the moment
OK、これは現時点では実際には解決できません
I don't even remember this
これすら覚えてない
there's a geoengineering we're almost done with
地球工学はもうすぐ終わります
You can come back after taking a nap
居眠りしても帰れる
That geoengineering is a pretty interesting thing
地球工学はかなり興味深いものです
Geoengineering has been talked about recently
最近地球工学が話題になっています
In fact, we have been talking about it for twenty or thirty years.
実際、私たちはこのことについて 20 年、30 年前から話し合ってきました。
the simplest and most feasible
最も単純で最も実現可能な
The first one is afforestation
一つ目は植林です
But afforestation is impossible without trees
しかし、木がなければ植林は不可能です
currently limited area
現在限定エリア
But if you have a solid word
でも、しっかりとした言葉があれば
Afforestation is a pretty good way
植林はとても良い方法です
Everything else has it's very serious problems
それ以外はすべて非常に深刻な問題を抱えています
But now everyone knows
でも今では誰もが知っています
we do air pollution
私たちは大気汚染を行っています
do the environment do the climate
環境をどうするか、気候をどうするか
We all know that the stratosphere adds some pollutants
成層圏が何らかの汚染物質を加えていることは誰もが知っています
add some lurking power
潜在的な力を追加する
like a volcano
火山のように
It is currently very feasible
現状ではかなり実現可能です
what's the only bad thing about it
唯一悪い点は何ですか
It is tantamount to putting a pollutant
汚染物質を投入するのと同じだ
Into a stratosphere to fight
成層圏へ行って戦う
another artificial this this
別の人工的なこれ
carbon dioxide
二酸化炭素
Well
良い
That is to say, from this direction
つまり、この方向から
he is he is a comparison to everyone
彼は誰とも比べられる存在だ
something you don't want to accept
受け入れたくないもの
but i'm guessing
でも私は推測します
ah
ああ
If say another ten or twenty years, the real problem
あと10年か20年かかるとしたら、本当の問題は
big
大きい
like this
このような
Well
良い
that that that
それはそれは
The problem of extreme weather becomes very big if
異常気象の問題は非常に大きくなる
Well
良い
there will be a united nations may
国連ができるかもしれない
authorized
認可された
do some experiments on this
これについていくつかの実験をしてください
Because of this experiment
この実験のせいで
nature has
自然は持っています
Experiments that have been given to us
私たちに与えられた実験
and the experiment is valid
そして実験は有効です
and his
そして彼の
It has very little side effects
彼の副作用は非常に最小限です
what is that
それは何ですか
It's a volcano
火山だよ
most everyone remembers
ほとんどの人が覚えている
Should be the one from the Philippines
フィリピン産のはず
year 1991
1991年
Volcanoes in Pingan Tubu
平安トゥブの火山
After that eruption, there are many things
あの噴火の後、色々なことがありました
its explosive
その爆発物
Enter the safe layer
安全層に入る
In 1992, 1993
1992年、1993年
global temperature
地球の気温
It has dropped by about 0.2 to 0.3 degrees
0.2～0.3度くらい下がった
two full years
丸二年
0.2 0.3 degrees down
0.2～0.3度下向き
you see a small volcano
小さな火山が見えます
Drop 0.2 0.3 degrees
ドロップ 0.2 0.3 度
The world has only increased by 0.6 degrees in 100 years
世界は100年間で0.6度しか上昇していない
so you just do
だからあなたはただそうするだけです
make three small volcanoes
3つの小さな火山を作る
the whole 100 years
100年間ずっと
can get it back
それを取り戻すことができます
So it seems to work
だからそれは可能だと思われる
just say now
今言ってください
you use a big plane
あなたは大きな飛行機を使います
or a big rocket
または大きなロケット
send this
これを送る
even with big balloons
大きな風船でも
Sending Pollutants to Stratosphere
汚染物質を成層圏に送り込む
not very difficult
あまり難しくない
this is promising
これは有望だ
So don't think it's hopeless
だから絶望的だと思わないでください
But
しかし
even if there is hope
たとえ希望があるとしても
I guess until the United Nations
国連までかな
when approved
承認されたとき
I'm afraid it will be decades later
数十年後になりそうで怖い
within these decades
この数十年のうちに
We in Taiwan should do debugging
台湾にいる私たちはデバッグをすべきです
That is to say, for such extreme weather
つまり、このような異常気象に対しては、
this flood drought
この洪水干ばつ
our government
私たちの政府
The real thing to say is that you should swim up and down
本当のことは、上下に泳ぐべきだということです
our government in this regard
この点に関して私たちの政府は
Measures against floods and droughts
洪水・干ばつ対策
really need to work hard
本当に頑張らなければいけない
I think this is quite important
これはかなり重要なことだと思います
At this time, I also want to talk a little bit
この際、私も少しお話したいと思います
Our Research on Extreme Weather
異常気象に関する研究
currently in this
現在この中にいます
There are still many places that do not fully agree
まだ完全に一致していないところがたくさんあります
Some people think that the result of what we do
一部の人々は、私たちが行ったことの結果を次のように考えています。
maybe a little too big
少し大きすぎるかもしれない
Because IBCC says
IBCCが言ってるから
The result obtained is relatively small
得られる結果は比較的小さい
Small quite a lot
小さいのがかなり多い
10 times smaller
有小10倍
So IBCC itself is now Evaluating this problem
そのため、IBCC 自体が現在この問題を評価しています。
they are not quite
彼らは完全ではありません
did not fully accept our view
私たちの見解を全面的に受け入れなかった
That is, the global temperature increases by one degree
つまり、地球の気温は1度上昇します
This strong drop will also increase a lot
この強い下落もまた大きくなるだろう
Especially where the tail is low
特に尻尾が低いところ
But I think this information
でも、この情報は、
more and more complete
ますます完成度が高くなりました
The model will get better and better in the future
モデルは今後もさらに改良されていくでしょう
We should have a more affirmative answer to this question from time to time.
この質問に対しては、比較的前向きな答えが得られることもあります。
took everyone's time
みんなの時間を費やした
so thank you all
だからみんなありがとう
ok
Ok
Thanks
ありがとう
Thank you Director Liu
劉監督、ありがとう
We still have ten minutes
まだ10分あります
I don't know if there is any problem doing it
やるのに問題があるかどうかはわかりません
to bring up for discussion
議論に持ち出す
A rare opportunity
滅多にない機会
please
お願いします
Small quite a lot
小さいのがかなり多い
thank you all
皆さん、ありがとうございました
Thanks
ありがとう
Sorry teacher
ごめんなさい先生
you just mentioned
あなたは今言いました
This is in the part that lowers greenhouse gases
これは温室効果ガスを削減する部分です
parts of some so-called earth factories
いわゆる地球工場の一部
The first part mentions reforestation
最初の部分では植林について言及しています
Well one thing we're curious about is
さて、私たちが興味を持っていることの 1 つは、
why must feel
なぜ感じなければならないのか
What you just said is that
あなたが今言ったことは、
There is an absolute relationship between tens and afforestation
十と植林には絶対的な関係がある
But the part like Taiwan
でも台湾っぽい部分は
There is a lot of farmland in the south-central
中南部には農地がたくさんある
Well, it's all presented now
さて、これですべてが提示されました
no situation
状況はありません
Then why is the afforestation part not considered in
では、なぜ植林の部分が考慮されていないのか。
part of flat land
平地の一部
For example, choose some fast-growing bridge trees
たとえば、成長の早い橋の木をいくつか選択します。
Then it is the substance itself to carry out photosynthesis
光合成を行うのは物質そのものです
It can consume a lot with the fixed open space
固定されたオープンスペースで多くの量を消費できます
carbon dioxide
二酸化炭素
If only some of the high ornamental value
観賞価値の高いものであれば
And it is a fast-growing large bridge tree
そして成長の早い大きな橋の木です
it is not itself a
それ自体ではありません
Is it a good solution?
それは良い解決策ですか?
Thanks
ありがとう
what you said is absolutely correct
あなたが言ったことは絶対に正しいです
not the only one you say
あなたが言うのは一人だけではありません
something you didn't notice
あなたが気づかなかった何か
That is to say, you put these things in Taiwan
つまり、これらのものを台湾に置いたということです。
It's all flat bottom to reforestation
植林までは平坦だ
that's also very very small
それもとてもとても小さいです
Taiwan is a small place after all
台湾は狭いところです
So our afforestation
そこで私たちの植林は、
The problem is the area
問題は面積だ
this is
これは
because you think about it
あなたがそれについて考えるから
A place like America
アメリカのような場所
You see how much it used to be covered by forest
かつてはどれだけ森林に覆われていたかがわかります
How much forest cover is there now
現在どれくらいの森林が広がっているのか
that is far
それは遠いです
unless somewhere like that
そういうところじゃない限り
that big place
あの大きな場所
Big places like America and China
アメリカや中国のような大きな場所
afforestation on a large scale
大規模な植林
You want such a large area of ​​afforestation
こんなに広大な植林地が欲しいのですね
food production must be
食料生産
pull it to the vegan stage
ヴィーガンの段階まで引き上げる
there is hope
希望がある
Otherwise, your area will never be enough
そうしないと、あなたの地域では決して十分ではありません
Taiwan you got it all
台湾、あなたはすべてを手に入れました
make a little
少し作る
ask Mr. Liu
劉さんに聞いてください
You use Taiwan's data to see the intensity of rainfall
台湾のデータを使用して降雨の強さを確認します
The relationship between temperature change and rainfall
気温変化と降水量の関係
Do you also do global
グローバルもやってるのかな
Global results are similar
世界的な結果は類似している
Yes
はい
our global results
私たちの世界的な結果
I remember the global result being slightly smaller than this
グローバルな結果はこれよりわずかに小さかったと記憶しています
No more than about 110 to 120
せいぜい110～120程度
In fact, it is like saying that we do lower-dimensional
実際、それは私たちが低次元のことをしていると言っているようなものです
better than Taiwan
台湾より良い
Excuse me, what did you just say about geoengineering?
すみません、地球工学について今何と言ったんですか？
Stratosphere plus some micro-arc melody thing
成層圏とマイクロアークのメロディーのようなもの
Ask him if there is any risk
何かリスクがあるかどうか彼に尋ねてください
Since you said he is currently more viable
彼は現在より生存可能であるとあなたが言ったので、
Why does the United Nations have to take some time to do something like this
なぜ国連はこのようなことをするのに時間がかかる必要があるのでしょうか
Many people have thought about the side effects
多くの人が副作用について考えたことがあるでしょう
i mean emphatically
強調して言います
nature is already doing
自然はすでにやっていること
you don't care if we do or not
私たちがやるかどうかは気にしません
The best ever
これまでで最高の
Actually is an interesting question
実は興味深い質問です
that is to say around
つまり周りに
about 700,000 years ago
約70万年前
That so-called one called
いわゆるあの人は
Poba TOBA
ポバ鳥羽
Poba this Indonesian one
ポバこのインドネシアのもの
A volcanic eruption in Indonesia
インドネシアで火山が噴火
What is that volcanic eruption claimed to be?
主張されている火山の噴火は何ですか?
It's what we've heard about volcanic eruptions anyway.
とにかく、それが火山の噴火について聞いたことです。
A hundred times that big volcano
その大きな火山の100倍
that big volcano erupted
あの大きな火山が噴火した
It is said that an earth
地球だと言われています
That creature would be that extinct one
その生き物はあの絶滅した生き物だろう
very big one
非常大的一個
I speak
私は話します
No
いいえ
70 super
70超
to 700,000 years
70万年まで
700,000 years ago
70万年前
to 700,000 years ago
70万年前まで
70 less
70未満
Yes do 70ë‚˜
はい、70나です
like that big volcano
あの大きな火山のように
after it explodes
爆発した後
It's been cold for a long time
久しぶりに寒いですね
Basically food production will have problems
基本的に食糧生産には問題が生じるだろう
there are also people
人もいます
the Big Bang 700,000 years ago
70万年前のビッグバン
that did happen
それは起こりました
that big bang is thought to be
ビッグバンは次のように考えられています
Humanity
人類
Just now from that Russi
今そのルッシから
3 million years to now
300万年後から現在まで
say human
人間と言う
There was barely a volcanic eruption 700,000 years ago
70万年前には火山の噴火はほとんどなかった
Vipassana
ヴィパッサナー
what we never said
私たちが決して言わなかったこと
you and i are not here
あなたも私もここにはいない
It is said that there is a theory that talks about people.
人を語る説があるという。
that is paired
それはペアになっています
Because of your pairing, you can give birth
君のペアリングだから 産めるんだ
The effective pairing minimum for pairing is reduced to almost
ペアリングのための有効なペアリングの最小値はほぼ減少します。
The worst is the worst estimate
最悪は最悪の見積もりです
There are only a thousand pairs left
残りは1000ペアのみです
so our genes
だから私たちの遺伝子は
Claiming to be our genes until now
今まで私たちの遺伝子だと主張して
The one with only a thousand pairs
千足しかないもの
Actually very outspoken
実はとても率直な
people are a bit outspoken
人々は少し率直です
our gene
私たちの遺伝子
Not too wide
広すぎない
that
それか
so the volcano erupted
それで火山が噴火した
the effects it causes
それが引き起こす影響
ah
ああ
as far as I can tell
私の知る限り
This small, medium-sized volcano
この中小規模の火山は、
we are pretty sure
私たちはかなり確信しています
then we
それから私たち
We use this artificial method
私たちはこの人工的な方法を使用しています
put this pollutant in
この汚染物質を入れてください
we can
我々はできる
put where we want
好きな場所に置きます
and again we want
そしてまた私たちは望んでいます
put it at the time you want to do it
やりたいときにそれを置く
and to the stratosphere
そして成層圏へ
as soon as we stop
私たちが立ち止まるとすぐに
stratosphere back to troposphere
成層圏から対流圏に戻る
We've all figured this out
私たちは皆これを数えました
is only two years
たった2年しかかかりません
That is to say, if you do something wrong
つまり、何か悪いことをした場合、
just two years
たった2年
like the one in the philippines
フィリピンのもののように
after entering
入った後
two-year effect
2年間の効果
Very small by the third year
3年目までにかなり小さくなる
not in the future
将来ではない
so this
したがって、この
i'm guessing
私は推測します
By the time
その時には
everyone is
みんなが
lazy
怠惰
That is to say, take the simplest method
つまり、最も簡単な方法を採用します
to solve
解決する
Teacher, what you just said
先生、今言ったこと
a hundred years
百年
drop in temperature
気温の低下
raise zero point six degrees
ゼロ点を6度上げる
Then ask this 0.6 degrees
じゃあこれを0.6度聞いてください
Let's say we start from
から始めるとしましょう
alpine
高山
When descending from high altitude to low altitude
高地から低地へ降下する場合
that temperature will naturally decrease
温度は自然に下がります
For example, from the Central Plains Institute
たとえば、セントラルプレーンズ研究所から
Going out to the city hall 101 may increase the temperature by several degrees
市役所101に出かけると気温が数度上がる可能性があります
So how is this 0.6 degree calculated?
では、この 0.6 度はどのように計算されるのでしょうか?
That is to say, the 0.6 degree you mentioned is one
つまり、あなたが言及した0.6度は1度です
what kind of thing
どのようなものですか
The second is to say
2つ目は、こう言うことです
The temperature decreases by one degree for every 100 meters increase in altitude
標高が100メートル上がるごとに気温は1度下がります
So are we this Global warming?
それでは、私たちは地球温暖化なのでしょうか？
Why use degrees to express
なぜ度数を使って表現するのか
what does this mean
これは何を意味するのでしょうか
that is
あれは
Will humans evolve as the temperature rises?
気温が上がると人類は進化するのか？
Maybe we can live with 40 degrees by then
その頃には40度でも生きていけるかもしれない
If you can't stand it, you'll hang up
我慢できないなら電話切るよ
So I have been thinking about this plus or minus two degrees C
そこで私はこのプラスマイナス 2 ℃について考えてきました。
Could it be an ad for a politician
政治家の広告だろうか
If for an ecologist
生態学者の場合
it represents a
それはを表します
What is the degree of coming and going?
行ったり来たりの程度はどの程度でしょうか？
i want to ask
聞きたいです
answer your questions
質問に答えてください
this degree
この程度
that is
あれは
the two of us
私達ふたり
There has to be a measure for these things
こういうことに対する対策が必要だ
Do you think why Qin Shihuang wanted to unify these things?
そもそもなぜ秦の始皇帝がこれらを統一しようとしたのか考えますか?
he has
彼は持っています
He is hoping to get something
彼は何かを得ることを望んでいる
something we can all accept
私たち全員が受け入れられるもの
to do this unit
この単元を行うには
So why do you say degrees
では、なぜ度を言うのでしょうか
This means that everyone is like European and American countries
つまり、誰もがヨーロッパやアメリカの国々と同じだということです
In fact, they have always been reluctant to use this degree
実際、彼らは常にこの学位を使用することに消極的でした
He used that Fahrenheit
彼は華氏を使用しました
He said to use that degree of Fahrenheit
彼はその華氏度を使うように言いました
So he doesn't use our speed
だから彼は私たちのスピードを利用しない
So it's just all together
だからそれはすべて一緒です
A unit that can communicate with each other
お互いに通信できるユニット
not nothing great
何も素晴らしいことではない
How much does the global temperature increase
地球の気温はどれくらい上昇しますか
that it is cool in different parts of the world
世界のさまざまな地域では涼しいということ
After it cools down, go to the average
冷めたら平均値へ
not like what you said
あなたが言ったことと違う
It's colder here
ここはもっと寒いです
It is actually fixed
実際には修正されています
Do it all over the world
世界中でやれよ
Tens of thousands of observations
数万件の観察
So 0.5 degrees is a big number
つまり、0.5度は大きな数字です
that number global temperature
その数字の地球の気温
It's not easy for you to get 0.5 degrees like this
このように0.5度を得るのは簡単ではありません
There was a French scholar named De Rijin
デ・リジンというフランスの学者がいました。
i forgot his french way
彼のフランス的なやり方を忘れてしまった
He is a hundred years old
彼は百歳です
Also stayed in China for a while De Rijin
中国にもしばらく滞在 デ・リジン
I remember he came up with a theory
彼が理論を思いついたのを覚えている
He said the earth is slowly cooling
彼は地球がゆっくりと寒くなっていると言いました
Is this the exact opposite?
これはまったく逆ですか？
Many people have mentioned this
多くの人がこれについて言及しています
Of course the most famous person
もちろん一番有名な人
His name is Milankovic
彼の名前はミランコビッチです
He's a Sirvia man
彼はシルビアの男です
Sirvia is now called the year before
シルヴィアは今では前年と呼ばれています
a place in yugoslavia
ユーゴスラビアの場所
it was in 1943
それは1943年のことでした
1920 during the war I remember
戦時中の1920年を思い出します
In 1943 a
1943年に
that is to say globally
つまり世界的に
Global temperature of ice and air versus flying ice and
氷と大気の地球の温度と流氷と
The theory of temperature change with ice and air
氷と空気による温度変化の理論
That is to say, the orbit of the sun and the earth
つまり、太陽と地球の軌道は、
some regular changes
定期的な変更
Make the earth ice and air once every 100,000 years
10万年に一度、地球を氷と空気にする
After it put forward this theory
この理論を提唱してから
It was raised in 1943 until it died
1943年に死ぬまで育てられた
It is the object of cancellation
キャンセルの対象です
People say it's unlikely to be true
人々はそれが真実である可能性は低いと言います
it says so
それはそう言う
Speaking of theory, it is quite complicated.
理論と言えば、かなり複雑です。
Now of course it doesn't look that complicated
もちろん、それほど複雑には見えません
But his theory lasted until 1978-80
しかし彼の理論は1978年から80年まで続いた
Get out the data of the sunken objects on the seabed
海底の沈没物のデータを取り出します
Let's find out all the previous temperatures
過去の気温をすべて調べてみましょう
As a result, I found out the previous temperature and put it together with his temperature.
その結果、前回の体温が分かり、彼の体温と合わせてみました。
almost identical
ほぼ同じ
So now everyone thinks he's great
だから今では誰もが彼を素晴らしいと思っている
But he's been dead for a long time
しかし彼は死んでから長い時間が経ちました
Your question was never answered
あなたの質問は決して答えられませんでした
That is to say, the glacier
つまり氷河です
it cools down very slowly
とてもゆっくりと冷えます
It will take almost 10 years for the temperature to drop
気温が下がるには10年近くかかる
but it heats up
でも熱くなる
not 10 years
10年ではない
That is to say, it takes 100,000 years for the temperature to cool down.
つまり、温度が下がるには10万年かかるということです。
It only takes 10,000 years to heat up
熱くなるのに1万年しかかからない
We are now in Jianbingheqi
私たちは今建平河斉にいます
Between the two soldiers and the flag
二人の兵士と旗の間
some people think
一部の人々は思う
The time when we were soldiers and flags
僕らが兵士で旗だった頃
It's been almost 13,000 years
約13,000年が経ちました
13000 years is quite a long time
13000年ってかなり長いよな
Should go back to the next pawn and flag
次のポーンとフラグに戻る必要があります
some people think so
そう思う人もいる
But most people think
しかし、ほとんどの人はこう考えます
Our next soldier and flag are still far away
次の兵士と旗はまだ遠い
still far
まだ遠い
Looks like at least 10,000 years
少なくとも1万年はかかるようだ
so
それで
i think there's every question
あらゆる疑問があると思います
Teacher Liu, I would like to ask
劉先生、お願いしたいのですが
Mitigation and adaptation are two different concepts
緩和と適応は 2 つの異なる概念です
But between the two
しかし二人の間では
actually related
実際に関連している
Recently, I noticed some related news reports
最近、いくつかの関連ニュースに気づきました。
especially france
特にフランス
Reduced cooling water capacity due to heat wave
猛暑による冷却水能力の低下
Then follow this operating specification
その後、この動作仕様に従ってください
it's running down load
ダウンロード中です
In the end, the lack of electricity has to import electricity from the UK
結局、電力不足のため英国から電力を輸入する必要がある
that means say
つまり言う
when
いつ
good slowing tool
優れた減速ツール
such as nuclear energy
原子力エネルギーなど
Hypothetically, this natural disaster or climate change factor
仮に、この自然災害や気候変動の要因は、
it might have a big discount on it
大幅な割引があるかもしれない
reduce its ability to slow down
減速能力を低下させる
Then I think more about the incident in Japan's Hudao Island.
それから私は日本の虎島での事件についてさらに考えます。
Even
平
Everyone is more impressed
みんなもっと感動してるよ
Of course Hu Dao is not necessarily related to climate change
もちろん胡道は必ずしも気候変動と関係があるわけではない
but at least it's a natural disaster
でも少なくともそれは自然災害だ
That is to say, nuclear energy is a very good mitigation tool
つまり、原子力は非常に優れた緩和ツールであるということです。
But under natural disaster
しかし、自然災害下では
it becomes a question mark
クエスチョンマークになる
Can it be used as a long-term view
長期的な視野で使えるのか
Can it be used as a mitigation tool
緩和ツールとして使用できるか
This is the first one
これが最初のものです
First
初め
first issue
第一個議題
from here
ここから
I want to derive the real thing I want to ask is
本当のことを導き出したい 聞きたいことは
For Taiwan
台湾向け
Because I saw some reports recently
最近いくつかのレポートを見たので
That is to say, according to the assessment of the world risk company
つまり、ワールドリスクカンパニーの評価によれば、
Taiwan is actually a high-risk area
台湾は実は高リスク地域だ
He said that it seems to include the number of three disasters
三大災害の数も含まれているようだという。
Seems like a 76 chance
確率は76のような気がする
There is probably such an assessment
そういう評価もあるかもしれない
Let's assume that back to the first premise I mentioned just now
先ほど述べた最初の前提に戻って考えてみましょう
Suppose so what I want to ask is to say
仮に、私が聞きたいのは、
For Taiwan from the perspective of climate change or natural disasters
気候変動や自然災害の観点から見た台湾にとって
Taiwan compared to the world average
台湾と世界平均との比較
Is it really a high-risk area?
本当に危険地域なのでしょうか？
If so
もしそうなら
In contrast to what Professor Liu mentioned just now
劉教授が今述べたこととは対照的に、
we are in mitigation
私たちは緩和中です
From 4kg to 12
4kgから12kgまで
In fact, it is disadvantageous in this respect
実はこの点では不利なのです
Then suppose we add this
次に、これを追加するとします
From the perspective of disaster
災害という観点から見ると
that's even worse
それはさらに悪いことです
So what I really want to ask is to say
それで私が本当に聞きたいのは、
The region of Taiwan compared to the world average
台湾の地域と世界平均との比較
From the perspective of climate change or natural disasters
気候変動や自然災害の観点から
Is it really as assessed by the risk company?
本当にリスク会社の評価どおりなのでしょうか？
is a high risk area
リスクの高い地域です
Thanks
ありがとう
good question
良い質問
But your question
しかし、あなたの質問は
basically i think what you said
基本的にはあなたが言ったことだと思います
that's true as far as i know
それは私が知る限り本当です
It's actually quite easy to answer
実は答えるのはとても簡単です
Think about how big our Taiwan is
私たちの台湾がどれほど大きいかを考えてみましょう
Four typhoons come every year
台風は毎年4回も来る
Almost all four typhoons will bring good rain
4つの台風はほぼすべて良い雨をもたらすでしょう
So the probability of a flood is
したがって、洪水の確率は、
It is deadly high compared to many countries
多くの国よりも高い
Especially for the entire Pacific Ocean
特に太平洋全体にとっては
This type of typhoon is stronger than the Atlantic typhoon
このタイプの台風は大西洋台風よりも強いです
average is strong
平均は強い
So we in Taiwan are rushing again
それで私たち台湾はまた急いでいます
The typhoon is coming towards us
台風が私たちに向かって来ています
Of course there is always someone worse than us
もちろん、私たちよりも悪い人は常にいます
In terms of typhoon, you go to the Philippines
台風と言えばフィリピンに行きますね
that's really what you do every year
それは本当に毎年やっていることです
Soak in water all day long
一日中水に浸しておく
we died hundreds of people
私たちは何百人もの人々を殺しました
we feel very unacceptable
私たちはとても受け入れられないと感じています
You go to see the people who die in typhoons every year in the Philippines
あなたはフィリピンで毎年台風で亡くなった人たちに会いに行きます
If he can reach less than a hundred people
100人未満の人に届けることができれば
he's overjoyed
彼は大喜びです
So the typhoon is actually very powerful
ということは、台風は実はとても強いのです
But the Philippines has fewer earthquakes than us
しかし、フィリピンは私たちよりも地震が少ないです
So Taiwan has many earthquakes and typhoons
台湾は地震や台風が多いので
what more
もっと何か
For our population, it is more worrying
私たちの国民にとって、それはさらに心配なことです
Then our Han disaster is stronger
そうすれば、私たちの漢の災害はより強力になります
Everyone thinks that 2500 mm of water is a lot of water for us a year
私たちにとって年間 2500 mm の水は多量の水だと誰もが考えています。
2500 mm lot of water
2500mmの水量
But because of the large population
しかし人口が多いので
Average water resources per person
1人当たりの平均水資源量
In fact, Taiwan ranks far behind in the world.
実際、台湾は世界ではかなり遅れています。
further back than mainland China as we know it
私たちが知っている中国本土よりもさらに奥
Mainland China seems to be shared by everyone
中国本土は誰もが共有しているように見える
twice as much as us
私たちの2倍
So yes ours is a high risk zone
はい、私たちの地域はハイリスクゾーンです
plus this earthquake
それに加えて今回の地震
Make this nuclear energy no way to use in Taiwan
この原子力エネルギーを台湾で使用できないようにする
It makes our action of slowing down in Taiwan even more
それが台湾での我々の行動をさらに遅らせることになる
looks very difficult
とても難しそうです
very difficult
非常に難しい
well because the time is just right
まあ、ちょうどいい時間が来たから
we are very grateful for this today
今日はとても感謝しています
Professor Liu Shaocheng is very strong
劉少成先生はとても強いです
I beg you ì˜ Athen Kaixing
お願いします 영 アセン・カイシン